<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>jpichon.net - Language_learning</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 22:57:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Anki &amp; Japanese Support Add-on on Fedora 28: "Something something 32 bit support"</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2018/12/anki-japanese-support-add-on-on-fedora-28-something-something-32-bit-support/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For a few months now, I've been having issues with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/"&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; Japanese support
add-on. Normally the add-on adds the readings automatically when creating new
cards, but lately that was failing with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
An error occurred in an add-on.
Please post on the add-on forum:
https://anki.tenderapp.com/discussions/add-ons

Traceback (most recent call last):
  File &amp;quot;/usr/share/anki/aqt/webview.py&amp;quot;, line 18, in run
    return unicode(self._bridge(unicode(str)))
  File &amp;quot;/usr/share/anki/aqt/editor.py&amp;quot;, line 462, in bridge
    &amp;quot;editFocusLost&amp;quot;, False, self.note, self.currentField):
  File &amp;quot;/usr/share/anki/anki/hooks.py&amp;quot;, line 32, in runFilter
    arg = func(arg, *args)
  File &amp;quot;/home/jpichon/.local/share/Anki2/addons/japanese/reading.py&amp;quot;, line 209, in onFocusLost
    n[dst] = mecab.reading(srcTxt)
  File &amp;quot;/home/jpichon/.local/share/Anki2/addons/japanese/reading.py&amp;quot;, line 76, in reading
    self.ensureOpen()
  File &amp;quot;/home/jpichon/.local/share/Anki2/addons/japanese/reading.py&amp;quot;, line 73, in ensureOpen
    raise Exception(&amp;quot;Please ensure your Linux system has 32 bit binary support.&amp;quot;)
Exception: Please ensure your Linux system has 32 bit binary support.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first I thought, meh, the rest works fine, and usually I don't need to add
the readings for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; word anyway, just the one that's new to me in the
sentence so that shouldn't take too much time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a few months to realise I wasn't creating new cards anymore, just
plopping them into a list of &amp;quot;cards to create when I have the time someday.&amp;quot;
Whoops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution, found via a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?pid=1681613#p1681613"&gt;ArchLinux thread&lt;/a&gt; is also dead simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
$ sudo dnf install libstdc++.i686 # Note the i686, that's the important bit!
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better get on with that word list now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 22:57:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2018-12-26:/blog/2018/12/anki-japanese-support-add-on-on-fedora-28-something-something-32-bit-support/</guid><category>Language_learning</category><category>japanese</category><category>open-source</category></item><item><title>Japan</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2015/04/japan/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm taking a year out to travel in Japan on a working holiday visa,
starting with a couple of months of studying the language some more. I
landed about 2 weeks ago. The school put me at a slightly higher level
than I had dared to hope and I am now learning new words, new
expressions, new nuances every day and generally having a tremendous
time :) I'm exactly where I want to be, doing and learning what I want
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm experimenting with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/132254976&amp;#64;N03/"&gt;posting pictures on
Flickr&lt;/a&gt; as I go, we'll
see how that works out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, note for future-self and other folks who are about to travel with
a cold: the so-called &amp;quot;ear planes&amp;quot; work great to avoid painful ear pain
on descent. I put them about 1h30 before landing on the second flight
and it was painless, quite a contrast with the previous flight 10 hours
earlier. Nasal spray helps a bit for comfort too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 00:35:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2015-04-18:/blog/2015/04/japan/</guid><category>Language_learning</category><category>japanese</category></item><item><title>DK House Sapporo</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2014/10/dk-house-sapporo/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to take a few minutes to give a shout out to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.e-guesthouse.com/eng/sapporo/"&gt;DK House in
Sapporo&lt;/a&gt;, as a great option
to get affordable housing for mediumish to longer stays in Japan. I
spent a month there in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DK house front" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2014/dk_house.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They specialise in short-term accommodations, normally starting from 3
months but if you want to stay for a shorter time like I did, you can
get in touch with them in advance and ask if it's ok. Despite sending my
queries in both Japanese and English, they replied in English only so
you don't need to be overly concerned about the language if your
Japanese isn't up to snuff yet :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The facilities are clean and the staff is always really helpful. As I
was staying only a few weeks I couldn't get a room with a private
bathroom, but it didn't turn out to be a problem. I never had to queue
for a shower. There's also a shared kitchen and a convenient laundry
room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rooms have a desk and a LAN port and I didn't have any major issues
with the Internet. As a backup I'd rented a &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.globaladvancedcomm.com/pocketwifi.html"&gt;pocket
wifi&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; and I was
glad to have it for network-intensive operations (ahem, devstack) or
when there was a bit too much contention. Also, there is no wireless in
the rooms. (If you're planning to spend a lot of time at that desk, you
may want to mentally prepare yourself for the fact that the chair was
not picked for its ergonomic qualities!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's some totally optional activities from time to time in the common
room, if you want to meet with the other residents. You're a few minutes
away from the tramway (市電) which leads you straight to the city centre
in 15 minutes, 3 konbinis (Lawson, Seven Eleven) and a super tasty ramen
place (てつや - I recommend the しょうゆ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you're used to luxurious super comfortable hotel mattresses and
spacious rooms I suppose you may be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DK House - Room" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2014/dk_house_room.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I'm really happy with my experience and heartily recommend
the place :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 17:54:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2014-10-08:/blog/2014/10/dk-house-sapporo/</guid><category>Language_learning</category><category>japanese</category></item><item><title>Adventures in Japan</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2012/06/adventures-in-japan/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In the middle of May, I went away for a couple of weeks in lovely
Fukuoka, Japan with the goal of expanding my knowledge of Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every weekday, I went to a language school,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.genkijacs.com"&gt;GenkiJACS&lt;/a&gt;. On the first day, my level was
accurately evaluated through a written test and interview, and on the
same afternoon I was put into a small class (5 people, myself included)
with students at a similar level from all over the world. The lessons
were held entirely in Japanese, with students' chitchat also happening
in Japanese -- a lovely atmosphere :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support from the staff, both by email during the preceding months and
during my stay, was top notch. The school also offers all sorts of
native language materials for students to borrow, though considering the
building was right above Mandarake, a manga/video games/DVD/etc shop, I
must say I mostly bought my own... :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stayed with a host family for the whole time, which was wonderful in
terms of language practice, making friends and experiencing varied
aspects of Japanese daily life. The perceived lack of independence made
me a bit twitchy at times though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concepts and vocabulary I learnt in and out of class have stuck well
so far -- the class format is very good, with lots of reviewing after a
new concept is introduced. In the end though, 2 weeks isn't enough time
to acquire that much new knowledge and I mostly treat the experience as
a very thorough level check. There are lots of conversations I had I
didn't realise were within my grasp. Because Japanese people are often
reluctant or unable to speak English (but always so nice and helpful!),
I had plenty of opportunities to practice in varied contexts and I'm now
a lot less shy about speaking in Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only 2 weeks, unfortunately there was little time for tourism,
though what I saw of Fukuoka City (Canal City, Kushida shrine and many
other temples, Oohori Park, my local yakitori izakaya and kappazushi...)
and the Fukuoka Prefecture (Dazaifu, Abura yama...) was delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely a wonderful experience. Study-wise, it was good for building
confidence and boosting motivation. It was also good for cheaply
acquiring plenty of contents in the language for practice... and making
new friends! :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wooden staircase in the forest" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2012/stairs.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 09:02:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2012-06-04:/blog/2012/06/adventures-in-japan/</guid><category>Language_learning</category><category>japanese</category></item><item><title>Learning Japanese | or, what to after the Michel Thomas Method</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/10/learning-japanese/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since listening to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/09/michel-thomas-method/"&gt;Michel Thomas Foundation
Course&lt;/a&gt;,
I've been intensifying my learning of Japanese. I'm not sure if I'm
learning in a sustainable way, but I'm enjoying the journey and will
ride the wave of motivation while it lasts :) In case I inadvertently
take a break and later want to come back to it, I'm going to write down
a few words on what I'm doing at the moment. Perhaps it'll be useful to
someone else too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="audio"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Audio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just finished the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Michel-Thomas-Method-Japanese-Advanced/dp/0340974591/"&gt;**Michel Thomas** Advanced
Course&lt;/a&gt;,
listening to one lesson in the bus every morning for the last while.
When I initially picked up the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/09/michel-thomas-method/"&gt;Foundation
Course&lt;/a&gt;, I
was hoping to learn some conversational Japanese without worrying about
the writing system ; however I really enjoyed the Advanced Course, which
taught me lots of things I either never learnt or more likely completely
forgot about since my initial stint at Japanese 10 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Michel Thomas Method is wonderful to build confidence, and the
Advanced course introduces you to many interesting grammar structures
using the -て and -た forms. I'm looking at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.japanesepod101.com/"&gt;Japanese Pod
101&lt;/a&gt; to get my audio fix now --
their content seems very good, despite the spammy feel of their sign-up
process. They actually offer a lot more than audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="grammar"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Grammar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get back to writing, a text book seemed appropriate to start learning
&amp;quot;proper.&amp;quot; I'm using the kana version of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/Japanese-Busy-People-Kana-Version/dp/4770030096/"&gt;**Japanese for Busy
People**&lt;/a&gt;,
mainly because I was eager to begin learning and it was available at my
local bookshop, and the Amazon reviews are good. Don't use the romaji
version. I'm enjoying it, there are plenty of exercises and they try to
use pictures as often as possible to help with retention, there's a CD
included with the book and some of exercises are audio (listen then
answer the questions in the book). It doesn't expand on grammar rules a
lot though, so one should make sure to go back to the grammar pages
regularly. For those not in a rush and with the money to spare, the
&lt;strong&gt;Genki&lt;/strong&gt; series &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tofugu.com/japanese-resources/genki/"&gt;looks to be fairly
good&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="kanji-vocabulary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Kanji &amp;amp; Vocabulary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I'm determined not to be discouraged by this time is
kanji. I got myself the very &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.whiterabbitpress.com/catalog/Japanese-Kanji-Flashcards-Series-2-Volume-1-p-16165.html"&gt;nice and sturdy **White Rabbit flash
cards**&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...Unfortunately after 40 or 50 kanji the ideograms, readings and
meanings stopped sticking into my head. It was time for context. See
below! The cards are still good to have around for recall, just not as a
single learning source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For vocabulary, I'm also testing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://iknow.jp/"&gt;**Iknow.jp**&lt;/a&gt;,
for which I luckily obtained a 4 month free subscription. It doesn't
focus on kanji as much as I'd like, but you learn to recognise words and
sentences with both audio and text, which is quite good. They have
several courses that together teach thousands of words of vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, to guide my learning of kanji I'm using the kanji list
recommendations for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jlpt"&gt;Japanese Proficiency Level
Test&lt;/a&gt;. Weakest level is N5 and
requires about 100 kanjis (reading a newspaper requires about 2000!).
I'm also curious at the &lt;strong&gt;TextFugu&lt;/strong&gt; approach of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.textfugu.com/free-lessons/"&gt;teaching the radicals
first&lt;/a&gt;, which seems to make
more sense to me and is another avenue to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="kanji-in-context"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Kanji in context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried a bilingual manga, which was a mistake (the English sticks out
more prominently than the Japanese, and probably doesn't encourage
focusing as hard on recognising kanjis). What I will warmly recommend
are the wonderful &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.whiterabbitpress.com/product.php?productid=16972&amp;amp;cat=0&amp;amp;page=1"&gt;**Japanese Graded Level Reader** book
series&lt;/a&gt;.
I'm going through Volume 0 at the moment (300 words/story, about 300
words of vocabulary overall) which read like simple children stories and
I find them as confidence building for reading as the Michel Thomas
method was for listening. Each volume contains 6 booklets entirely in
Japanese, in which new concepts and words are repeated a lot so that
between the repetition and the pictures, the reader can figure out the
meaning of most of the story. It's very cute, and you learn about
Japanese culture as well. Very much recommended. There are many volumes
for different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I read one of the aforementioned &amp;quot;Reader&amp;quot; booklets, I add the
kanji and grammar expressions I don't yet know to a set of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ankisrs.net/"&gt;**Anki**&lt;/a&gt; flashcards, with the help of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jisho.org/"&gt;jisho.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.guidetojapanese.org/learn/grammar"&gt;Tae Kim's guide to Japanese
grammar&lt;/a&gt; if needed.
Anki's a wonderful piece of software! You can synchronise for free
between different machines to make sure the Spaced Repetition algorithm
keeps up no matter where you go through the cards, and it has a Maemo
port (ankiqt900), among many other platforms. I'm still figuring out how
best to make cards ; sometimes having the kanji on its own, other times
including context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I bought the first volume of a manga I'm interested in that has
furigana, and I'm still exploring what's the best way to read, and
learn, and create flash cards out of it without ruining the flow, losing
interest or having to make 20 flashcards out of every bubble... (ahem!)
I don't expect the process to be fast in any case :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;勉強しましょう。(&amp;lt;- let's begin testing the unicode resilience of this
lil' blog!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 20:19:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2011-10-24:/blog/2011/10/learning-japanese/</guid><category>Language_learning</category><category>japanese</category></item></channel></rss>