<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>jpichon.net - career</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2010 13:39:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Book review: Women don't ask: Negotiation and the gender divide, by Babcock and Laschever</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/04/women-dont-ask/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I discovered this book thanks to Valerie Aurora, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://valerieaurora.org/ask.html"&gt;looking up her
website&lt;/a&gt; after hearing her speak
at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.skycon.skynet.ie/2007/"&gt;SkyCon '07&lt;/a&gt;. It's taken me a
while to get around to reading it but it was very worthwhile. I would
recommend reading Val's review of it, which I linked above and will link
again because &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://valerieaurora.org/ask.html"&gt;it's a really good
review&lt;/a&gt;. I don't know if the book
has &amp;quot;changed&amp;quot; my life just yet, but it's certainly been making me think
a hell of a lot, it's made me more observant of the subtle -- or
non-subtle I had totally missed until now because they seem so &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot;
-- ways in which girls and boys are treated and the expectations that
are put upon them from early on, and how people (of both genders) react
to things differently depending on the gender of the person who said or
did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed all the studies described all along the book, as well
as the insights the book provides in understanding where a lot of social
expectations and pressures come from and how they shape and affect how
people, including myself, behave or react to others' actions. Knowing
this is helpful to understand people's behaviour better and hopefully
would encourage the readers, no matter their gender, to negotiate better
for themselves. I look forward to having a look at &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Ask-Women-Really-Power-Negotiation/dp/0749927844/"&gt;Ask for
it&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;,
the follow-up book which focuses on giving actual strategies to improve
negotiation skills.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2010 13:39:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-04-24:/blog/2010/04/women-dont-ask/</guid><category>Misc</category><category>book review</category><category>career</category></item><item><title>Book review: The Passionate Programmer, by Chad Fowler | The Passionate Programmer: Creating a remarkable career in software development</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/02/passionate-programmer/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I heartily recommend this book to anyone who wants to take control of
their career, cares about their career, or is unhappy about where they
currently are. Change and remarkable careers, like anything else, don't
just happen to you, you have to work hard (and have fun!) to make them
happen.This book gives you ways to achieve that, while having fun and
staying true to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed reading it, it helped me structure and articulate my
thoughts better around some ideas I hold on career development. I found
it to be very encouraging, in nudging or kicking the reader's ass to be
more active in building one's career consciously (honing a sense of
business, mentoring, automating, personal brand...) and watching out for
the traps along the way (over-specialisation, obsolescence, office
politics and perception...). The format is really good as well: a
multitude of very short chapters, usually 2 to 4 pages long thus perfect
for a quick, self-contained read whenever you have a few minutes, with
plenty of time afterward to mull over the ideas brought up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every chapter ends with an &amp;quot;Act on it&amp;quot; section which gives you tips,
food for thought and calls to action related to the chapter contents. I
always have a problem with (good) books that contain this kind of list,
because if I wait to actually have/make the time to do what they ask me
to do, I never finish reading them. I usually deal with this by reading
the book from start to finish once, then (hopefully) giving it another
read slower, later on, taking the time to follow through the action
items. This was my first read. I still got quite a lot out of it: a few
book references, new cool ideas to explore and a sense of confidence and
reinforcement when this confirmed or fleshed out some of my beliefs and
the path I have set onto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is divided into 5 sections: Choosing your market, investing in
your product (that's you, by the way ;)), executing, marketing and
maintaining your edge. There are a few essays by other people inserted
here and there that offer refreshing point of views, real-life examples
or case studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book can be bought &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pragprog.com/titles/cfcar2/the-passionate-programmer"&gt;from the
publisher&lt;/a&gt;
in addition to any good bookstore. I really enjoy the Pragmatic
Bookshelf books and they sometime have cool promotional offers, so I
tend to get the books from them directly and recommend it to people. :)
There are a few chapter extracts as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2010 18:38:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-02-20:/blog/2010/02/passionate-programmer/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>book review</category><category>career</category></item></channel></rss>