<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>jpichon.net - ireland</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 21:58:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>ShipItCon 2024</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2024/08/shipitcon-2024/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;To avoid taking a year again to (fail to) put my notes together, I decide to do
it quickly and stick to a few thoughts and highlights. The 2024 edition of
&lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/"&gt;ShipItCon&lt;/a&gt; happened today. This year's theme was "Flow." Many speakers
mentioned ownership when talking about ways to reach flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't attended many conferences in the last couple of years, but maybe 90%
of the people I talked to were also meeting their co-workers face-to-face for
the first time at this event, despite working together for years. At least
three different companies. I found it interesting. It doesn't look like there
are many opportunities for teams to meet outside of conferences at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ShipItCon welcome slide" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2024/shipitcon2024.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;DevOps Topologies 10 years on: what have we learned about silos, collaboration, and flow? (Matthew Skelton)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker kindly summarised his findings both at the start and the end of the
talk: decouple teams and tech (not just defining an org structure, something
more dynamic), but diffuse learning across the company (that can take the form
of Lunch and Learns, blogs, Communities of Practice, guides, etc...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading recs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gene Kim's books (the Phoenix Project, Accelerate, ...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SODOR, the State Of DevOps Reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Organisation, Flow, and Architecture (Sam Newman)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an incredibly dynamic and engaging speaker! The theme was generally how to
reduce handoffs, which happens particularly when organisation are siloed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conway's law: An organisation design systems that replicate the communication
structure of that organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you have Taylorism-inspired silos with e.g. separate
front-end/back-end/DB teams, the system will reproduce that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution is feature-based teams (micro-services are good to enable full
ownership). Durable as opposed to initiative-based teams are also better as
long-lived teams make better decisions about trade-offs (e.g. incurred tech
debt, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Data Driven Decisions to Improve Testing Flows (Heather Reid)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using data to take risks. Differentiating between reversible and not reversible
risks. The speaker used various examples based on her own experiences to
illustrate the principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example: closing an old bug to remove noise is easily reversible if it
turns out it shouldn't have been closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 1000s of users report a problem, it can feel like millions/all of your users
are hitting the problem. But maybe when you look at the data it's 0.6% of the
userbase, which is still bad but not world-ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or a really bad bug affecting 6 users using that phone model (out of millions)
can probably be closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prioritise accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Observability 2.0 and other things (Charity Majors)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The title isn't on the agenda and I forgot to write it down!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tip for how to supercharge your career: join a high-performing team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineering should own the code in production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observability is a property of complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observability-driven development means looking at your dashboards (as opposed
to waiting for alerts/paging to bring them up). It's a constant conversation
with code (including unstructured logs, not just metrics, because they provide
CONTEXT). (Higher level: structured logs with trace ids you can follow end to
end.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Establishing a culture of ownership and observability at Phorest (Paweł Malon and Paul Dailly)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the speakers use Honeycomb which is the observability platform
of the previous speaker. It was like seeing practical examples of the concepts
detailed in the previous talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of engineering owning the code all the way to production came up
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And also, of linking engineering workflows to observability: deploying a change
and seeing what difference it makes, and conversely using the insights gained
from observing software behaviour on prod to find new bugs/improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a lot of metrics does create issues with the cost of storing all of that
data, which is where sampling helps, although the speakers talked about the
other problems you then have to deal with when sampling and how to manage them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Go With The Flow? (Vessy Tasheva)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play is a component of flow. Venn diagram of Play and Environment with Flow
where the circles meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environment: must be safe even if there are constraints/discomfort. E.g. a
leader having your back when working on a challenging project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play is a way to be more authentic and creative. "Being" (which respects focus
time) vs "Reacting" (which breaks flows and creates defensiveness).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Flow-etry in Motion: Navigating Cascades of Threat Data (Claire Burn)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting twist to the talk! When the speaker submitted it, it was supposed
to be about how their pivot to using Kubernetes and Google Cloud Platform
enabled better flow in the team. But by the time the conference happened, they
had reverted back to AWS and EC2!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no "peak flow" to be found because Kubernetes wasn't the right tool
to solve their problems (they needed finer grained OS control).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considerations around Learning Curve vs Velocity, especially when working as a
smaller team (4 people). The management debt became too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did end up keeping Kotlin from this experiment, good for integration with
other Java projects in the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The impact of Flow on various aspects of work (Panel discussion)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beat_Saber"&gt;Beat Saber&lt;/a&gt; as a way to get into flow 😂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed teams are good for making the implicit explicit. Managing based on
outcomes. The additional flexibility is good for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honeycomb has a quarterly "everyone works from home" week, up to the CEO. It's
good to get distance from processes, etc. (I thought that was a refreshing
contrast to all the Return To Office talk from the last couple of years.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many problems are socio-technical: need a combination of tech and people
solutions, not just one or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Harnessing Developer Insights to maximise flow (Mihai Paun and Alma Tarfa)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learned helplessness in companies: "we've always done it this way" "that's
never going to work here."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the picture of the Iceberg of Ignorance, from &lt;a href="https://www.corporate-rebels.com/blog/iceberg-of-ignorance"&gt;Corporate
Rebels&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Iceberg of Ignorance" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2024/iceberg-ignorance.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papercuts affecting flow tend not to surface in retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Plan - Do (gather data) - Check (target condition) - Act&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, they found their dev team struggled to reach flow state because of
the number of meetings, so they decided to try setting up two no-meetings day
(Monday, Wednesday) then gather data to see if that helped. Everyone involved
in the four steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small changes toward reaching the bigger goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders: be gardeners, not mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From MLOps to AI Systems (Jim Dowling)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most AI systems don't ship. This hasn't changed in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MLOps, LLMOps. He explained when he teaches a ML course, his students complete
an AI project from scratch in 2 weeks. It doesn't need to be as complicated as
30+ steps diagrams/consultants make it out to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While looking for a link to the course, I came across this &lt;a href="https://www.hopsworks.ai/post/mlops-to-ml-systems-with-fti-pipelines"&gt;detailed
article&lt;/a&gt; that goes into the details of the talk if that is of interest. And
includes a link to the students' projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Finding personal flow (Patrick Kua)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal flow usually comes from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adding value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a lot of ownership (with support)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a sense of progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;applying the team's strengths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker used past experiences to illustrate various kind of very different
environments that can lead to good flow. This actually linked back nicely to
Vessy's earlier talk as well: challenging projects but in a safe
environment/with support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anecdotes I liked was when he was trying to remove himself as a
bottleneck in a large project, he broke down the features, and asked if anyone
would step up as feature leads for each of those. People had no problem
volunteering and that also links back to ownership again. And feature-based
teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of putting up notes early is that the recordings are not yet
available!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Julie Pichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 21:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2024-08-30:/blog/2024/08/shipitcon-2024/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>ireland</category></item><item><title>UXDX 2018</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2019/10/uxdx-2018/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whoops! Clearly I'm never going to finish writing up my notes for the
conference last year. Better post what I got even if incomplete, before the
next one begins :-) I couldn't get a discounted ticket this year and won't be
attending. Have fun, everyone there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be able to attend &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://uxdxconf.com/"&gt;UXDX&lt;/a&gt; this
year as well, thanks to a discounted ticket and my employer kindly allowing me
the day off. The venue was again the RDS, with the lovely room that's lined up
with actual real books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UXDX is an interesting conferences, that aims to bring down barriers between
User Experience and Developer Experience people. The conference has expanded
this year, now covering two days. I was happy to see some issues I had with the
conference last year resolved. For example, although the stated goal is to
bring together UX and DX people, improve collaboration, etc, the tracks were
completely separate. Worst for the DX-centred talks, the &amp;quot;room&amp;quot; was a stage at
the back of the exhibition hall and all the noise that entails. This year, the
separation between the two tracks was labelled &amp;quot;Vision&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Execution&amp;quot; which
made it easier to have talks mixing everything together, and also the Execution
room had a proper room with doors that close. The room was larger than the
section assigned last year too, and always full whenever I peeked in. Both
tracks were always busy. The exhibition hall seemed pretty empty outside of the
breaks, but there were plenty of those - staggered to lessen the lunch/coffee
rush.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="51%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="49%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td rowspan="2"&gt;&lt;img alt="Library room" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2018/RDS.jpg" style="width: 330.0px; height: 247.50000000000003px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td rowspan="2"&gt;&lt;img alt="Books" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2018/RDS_books.jpg" style="width: 330.0px; height: 247.50000000000003px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a handful of talks I was looking forward to, some met my expectations
and others turned out different. Many other good surprises. I'll summarise some
of the talks I enjoyed the most and only include my key takeaways for
others. This doesn't mean any of it was the actual point or meat of the talk,
more like the insights that were new to me personally and that I'll be
ruminating on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-one"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="micro-frontend-architecture-luca-mezzalira-dazn"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Micro Frontend Architecture | Luca Mezzalira (DAZN)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the day in the Execution room (it sounds a bit dramatic phrased like
this) and didn't really know what to expect with this talk, but it may have
ended up being my favourite one. The speaker stated his problem clearly - how
to make it work with hundreds of distributed developers/teams - and also noted
that the solution he came up with challenges common software development
wisdom, but to keep an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is to share absolutely nothing. Not even a button. &lt;strong&gt;Don't&lt;/strong&gt; create a
library of shared components, like headers. Really, how often does your header
change anyway? Trust your developers. They can duplicate and maintain this. The
goal is to minimise dependencies. Don't centralise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest is structured based on &amp;quot;Domain-Driven Development.&amp;quot; Each team has
their own domain (e.g. Catalogue, Subscription, Payment, ...) and completely
independent technology stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quicker on-boarding, because you only need to understand your own domain
deeply&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to scale teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom for developers to innovate and own something end-to-end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also mentioned the positive impact on turnover. In London, it's apparently
not uncommon for developers to change company every year, year and a half. This
makes it easy to try new technology which is often the main reason to jump
ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are frameworks that enable this nowadays, like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://single-spa.js.org"&gt;single-spa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://frint.js.org"&gt;frint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="planning-your-agile-architecture-will-demaine-fat-llama"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Planning your Agile Architecture | Will Demaine (Fat Llama)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an excellent talk, and well delivered as well. The speaker described
the steps you may want to follow to modernise your application and enable a
more agile architecture, from lessons learnt first hand through different
companies. If I had to undertake a project like this I think I'd find the
slides or recording again to refresh my memory first, but for today my key
takeaways would be that this is a long process that you want to tackle
iteratively, so that you can continue to deliver &lt;strong&gt;business value&lt;/strong&gt; along the
way. No one will let you just take off and deliver nothing new for 8 months
while you rewrite the thing from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have solid foundations in place (monitoring, feature flags, ...) before
starting. Take your time and do it right the first time or they won't let you
migrate more services!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point I found interesting: create a gateway for the clients, the things
that you can't roll back like mobile apps. Even if it's just a proxy to start
with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="embracing-empathy-tim-hudson-adyen"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Embracing empathy | Tim Hudson (Adyen)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pie charts bad. Bar charts good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Also, look into the Design Sprint / Design Sprint 2.0 books.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="solving-problems-to-build-a-compelling-product-deborah-clarke-cartrawler"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solving Problems to Build a Compelling Product | Deborah Clarke (Cartrawler)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User research is vital but not the only important thing. Combining with other
incentives can lead to better focus and great breakthroughs. Innocuous, small
moments of delight can increase your conversion rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-journey-from-complexity-reducing-technical-debt-fabrizio-fortunato-ryanair"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Journey from Complexity: Reducing Technical Debt | Fabrizio Fortunato (Ryanair)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting to follow the evolution of the RyanAir front page over the decades!
Some tidbits I found of interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact of page load. Any speed increase has a direct impact on revenue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use &amp;quot;micro-pages.&amp;quot; Concept similar to micro-frontend except it relates
to full pages, each page is its own app. So everyone is only responsible for
their own page independently, and loosely coupled. Single SPA per page, that
can be released independently but still has shared components (interesting
contrast with micro-frontend above).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They eventually wrote two different apps for mobile and web, as optimising
for one over the other never quite worked and only served in increasing
complexity. Now optimised for each flow. Still haven't decided whether to use
mobile or web format on tablets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use GraphQL, serverless, Brotli.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="design-and-prototyping-david-hoang-one-medical"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Design and prototyping | David Hoang (One Medical)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prototypes should be low cost and provide high insights. The goal is
learning. Having a prototype together with a vision/roadmap is powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Validating&amp;quot; a prototype or design is about gaining insights. About
learning. Not about proving something right or wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design is not magic, it's a rigorous process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include User Testing in every sprint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prototyping is successful if you get &lt;strong&gt;insights&lt;/strong&gt; that provide &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; to
your user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examples related to medical applications were compelling. From paper
(e.g. stuck onto a 3d printed watch model, to test for smart watches ahead of
releases), to powerpoint, to node-based prototyping, to Figma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-tools-we-use-challenging-dogma-in-the-design-process-emmet-connolly-intercom"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The tools we use: Challenging dogma in the design process | Emmet Connolly (Intercom)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools influence output, and can even generate trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use these tools and remain sceptical, don't let the tools push you around and
end up with a design monoculture (noticeable in the history of the web).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Design Ops&amp;quot; - a concept I hadn't heard of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ensuring-the-success-of-your-remote-engineering-team-panel"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ensuring the Success of your Remote Engineering Team | Panel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked that the conference kept the talks to 30 minutes, but I think
that's one case where it would have been better to get an extended timeslot,
maybe 45 minutes. As it stands even with only two panelists (+ one moderator)
we barely had time to scratch beyond the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping a budget for internal face-to-face interactions, some kind of annual
get-together has a great impact on morale and engagement and pays for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of saving on office space is not the point (numbers like
€17,000/person in Dublin, €11,000/person in Sligo were mentioned). Talent is
the point. Working remotely helps to attract and retain people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onboarding strategies were briefly touched on. One of the companies hires
mainly senior people with 10y+ experience while the other also hires new grads
so the strategies are different. It's great if you can get people to HQ for
this, makes sure they understand the company's values and culture, and also the
tools at their disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep people connected, having non-work related communication channels like a
#showyourdesk Slash channel or &amp;quot;whose view is better this week?&amp;quot; can help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time zones are a challenge for global meetings. Some expectation that you will
go the extra mile for the business, since you are not tied to a regular 9 to 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were concerns about working from home and whether people are really
working. In general the opposite seemed to be a concern for the panelists: when
people work from home you can't see the black bags under their eyes, or if
people are stuck. People know working from home is a privilege and work hard to
prove themselves. One of the companies measures employee productivity to make
sure they don't burn out - though you have to be very careful about how you
measure people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret sauce is flexibility. Work is only one part of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about accountability and self-determination? Decisions should be made by
the person who needs to. Empower people. Get that right. Measure what you want
success to look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regard to people not contributing, teams are tight and it becomes obvious
who is and who isn't. You do need to be more proactive in searching for
information with remote teams. One-on-one meetings every two weeks to touch
base. They are still refining the process. Seven seems to be a magic
number, you can see if people are performing for any type of team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="accessibility-brian-dalton-aer-lingus"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accessibility | Brian Dalton (Aer Lingus)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I missed the beginning but seeing how a user who relies on accessibility
features uses a computer and navigates the Internet is always powerful. Lots of
work to be done still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From keyboard to navigation to simple, silly things like &amp;quot;times shown in red
are not available.&amp;quot; Label your fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="five-phrases-that-shout-your-agile-isn-t-scaling-tony-grout-atlassian"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Five phrases that shout your agile isn't scaling | Tony Grout (Atlassian)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agile manifesto 17 years ago didn't talk about how to scale it! From 17 to
70000 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some interesting suggestions that challenge conventional wisdom. My favourite:
it's well-known that smaller teams are more productive. Studies have shown that
teams of 9 to 16 people were 6% less productive than teams of 5 to 9. However,
if you decide to make 2 teams instead you now have &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt; the unpredictability
because you've added a dependency on another team. Think carefully, run the
experiment to see if bigger teams may be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage people to think about &amp;quot;teams&amp;quot; over &amp;quot;team.&amp;quot; For example, if the UI
team is currently the bottleneck, instead of engineering twiddling their thumbs
or overengineering something while they wait, perhaps they could create tooling
to help the team. That slows them down and helps the other team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One team working faster can cause everyone else to go slower. For example, a UI
team wanting to be pixel perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those closest to the problem should make the decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="kessel-run-a-digital-transformation-story-within-the-world-s-largest-bureaucracy-adam-furtado-kessel-run-u-s-air-force"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Kessel Run: A Digital Transformation Story within the World's Largest Bureaucracy | Adam Furtado (Kessel Run / U.S. Air Force)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting choice for a closing keynote for day one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transformation described is absolutely incredible. The speaker spent a fair
amount of time at the beginning to explain the current state of things,
years/decades of risk aversion leading to becoming unable to adapt to change
and thus less safe. Twelve to fifteen years to go from an idea to something in
the users' hands, 96% of project behind schedule or over budget, 40% never
delivered... They went to Pivotal, who helped them to learn about modern
software development practices, devops, etc but more importantly how to change
the culture. Now deploying is a non-event and they went from 10 years to 120
days for delivering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's truly inspiring and the project they presented as an example showed the
real-world benefits: allowing soldiers to stay safe at home and with their
family rather than go on months-long refuelling missions around the world,
thanks to streamlining the refuelling planning process with
software. Definitely a worthy goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was however a bit strange to hear about software described as a
differentiator and weapon to cultivate on the battlefield, and how to improve
warfare. I suppose keynotes are meant to make you think rather than just give
you warm fuzzy feelings, and this talk sure fit the bill!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Courtyard" class="align-center" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2018/RDS_courtyard.jpg" style="width: 600px; height: 450px;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-two"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day Two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was just as interesting, too bad I left it too long to get the rest of my notes
together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 07:24:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2019-10-07:/blog/2019/10/uxdx-2018/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>Ireland</category></item><item><title>PyCon Ireland 2014</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2014/11/pycon-ireland-2014/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Together with a couple of colleagues, I wrote a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://community.redhat.com/blog/2014/11/pycon-ireland-2014-report/"&gt;short report about
PyCon Ireland
2014&lt;/a&gt;.
Once again the conference was a lot of fun and I'm looking forward to
the 2015 edition! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 08:56:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2014-11-20:/blog/2014/11/pycon-ireland-2014/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>ireland</category><category>python</category></item><item><title>Evolving Open-Source Night | Open-Source Night - June</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2013/07/evolving-open-source-night/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The monthly Open-Source night experiment continues. On Wednesday, June
19th we had the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/06/open-source-night-june/"&gt;June edition of Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.technomancy.org/"&gt;Rory&lt;/a&gt; gave us a
slightly-longer-than-15-minutes talk on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openstreetmap.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, and the kind of
contributions the project welcomes (data data data, really!). I was the
only one to volunteer for a lightning talk, in stark contrast with the
last event where we had multiple ones both by people attending
open-source night and network people who happened to be visiting the
hackerspace at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than doing an on-topic talk about an open-source project, I did a
meta-talk about Open-Source Night itself and different ways in which it
could evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I make no secret that I don't think open-source night works very well in
its current format. My goal (and measure for success) is to help people
actually get started contributing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: if you were at my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedotconf.wordpress.com/whos-speaking/julie-pichon/"&gt;deep dive on contributing to
open-source&lt;/a&gt;
and planning on attending the next open-source night, please do come!!
This all just means that I think there are things that can be improved
:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reminder-the-current-format"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reminder: The current format&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're currently meeting on the 3rd Wednesday of the month. The event
usually starts with two 15 minutes talk, ideally one on the life of
open-source (e.g. licences, version control, IRC, using the
command-line...) and one on how to contribute to a specific project.
Then there's a number of 5-minutes-long-or-less lightning talks where
people can introduce the project they will be working on during the
evening. Then people break into groups or independently work on an
open-source project of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or that's the idea anyway. The talks usually work well and are
inspiring, though they tend to run overtime and then people have trouble
sitting at a table and doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are my thoughts and ideas as to where open-source night might go
in the future. These are not plans. I would like to hear feedback from
interested people - attendees, would-be attendees, other organisers and
thoughtful passerbys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="topics-general-open-source-vs-project-specific"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics: General open-source vs Project-specific&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see value in both topics, but perhaps attendees and would-be attendees
favour one or the other, both, or neither? I haven't really heard much
on this, what people find most useful. I think the project specific
talks at least are interesting for both newcomers and established
contributors, to see how other projects do things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe 15 minutes is a good amount of time to get an overview, get
inspired and get ideas. And not get too bored if already familiar with
the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could see the value and how efficient it would be to focus on one
project for a full session and guide people through contributing to it.
However I can also see how it could be offputting to people not
particularly interested in the project (e.g. &amp;quot;I don't use that distro,
why should I bother attending?&amp;quot;). Perhaps as separate, off-shoot events
if people are interested in leading that kind of session (get in
touch!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="topics-all-kind-of-contributions-vs-focusing-on-code"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics: All kind of contributions vs Focusing on code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I try really hard to emphasise (and encourage speakers to
do the same) all the kinds of contributions that can be made - and are
well needed! - even though my own experience lies in code-based
contributions. Maybe I should give up on being inclusive and focus on
what I know best, rather than try to be all things to all people?
Code-focused open-source events could go from learning to program to
fixing a bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I was hoping people would step up to talk and encourage people
to join their area of interest (I think we have e.g. experienced
open-source translators around...) but that hasn't happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually a point where someone came up to me after the talk and
said straight off they really liked the breadth of contributions demoed
during the talks, in particular mentioning &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/05/open-source-night-may/"&gt;last month's
talk&lt;/a&gt; by Guilherme
on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openmandriva.org"&gt;OpenMandriva&lt;/a&gt; that did a great job
showing how someone can help, in a multitude of ways, even if they're
not all that confident in their coding skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="format-more-course-like"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Format: More course-like?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of days before the June OSS Night I was pointed to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://opensource.com/life/13/6/learning-program-open-source-way"&gt;this
article on a really, really interesting summer course on learning to
program the open-source
way&lt;/a&gt;.
That's a really cool concept. Should we entertain the thought of doing
something similar during open-source night? e.g. A session on learning
how to use version control with exercises, very workshop like, one
month, some other topic the next one, etc.?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not, but something to consider as a separate course with a
shorter timeline. A course with one session a month will lose people and
have little momentum. Is this the kind of things people have an interest
in learning?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="format-doing-vs-listening-talking"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Format: Doing vs Listening/Talking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal with this event is still to get people started contributing. I'm
not interested in organising a monthly night of talks. Finding speakers
is stressful. If the talks aren't followed by some contributing action,
to me the event is failing and I'm not interested in continuing to
organise it. There are plenty of events around Dublin already where
people can meet, talk tech and shoot the breeze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regard to open-source related talks, I think that's already handled
well by the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.linux.ie"&gt;ILUG&lt;/a&gt; folks, who are now keen to
set them up regularly again under the new chairmanship :) And we can
join forces if that's the most attractive part of the event to folks. If
your main interest is in having a regular night of open-source talks,
get in touch and I'll be happy to help you have this in Tog. I'd attend
with pleasure anyway, I'm just not interested in organising it and go
speaker-hunting every 3 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still believe we can make something really cool happen by putting in
the same room people experienced in open-source together with newcomers
interested in contributing. So I'm not giving up yet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's of course also the timeframe issue: with or without talks, an
evening of maybe 3 hours is not a lot of time to accomplish something.
Maybe we could (also/instead?) have events on Saturdays? And/or week-end
workshops, Friday eve to Sunday?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOWEVER, in any case an evening is still enough time to accomplish
&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, get started, get the momentum going, get unblocked and
finish your contribution later at the week-end, in your own time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="you-why-are-you-here-anyway"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;You: Why are you here anyway*? ;)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* Or why weren't you? :) I'm just as interested in the answer to that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in learning how to contribute? Interested in helping
and mentoring newcomers? What were you hoping this evening would be
about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then invited people to have a productive discussion with me about this
should they wish to, somewhat contradicting my own doing vs talking rant
:-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free and welcome to continue the discussion in the comments
or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/about/"&gt;by email&lt;/a&gt;, I would love to pick
more brains and exchange ideas about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="django-challenge"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Django challenge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid the talk being entirely meta (and in case people didn't care
that much about all the blah blah blah and more about the doing!), I
issued a challenge to attendees as well: this evening, run the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; unit tests suite. If that's
something you're set up for, it'll take 2 minutes. If you're familiar
with the concept but don't have all the dependencies set up yet it'll
take 20 minutes. If this is all new to you it might take 2 hours, but
what you learn you'll be able to reuse when you start working on a
project you care about in the future, and it means it'll take less long
then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person took me up on it and it took them 10 minutes. This shows how
possible it is to actually get the ball rolling during open-source
night, get people to realise they're not that far away from a first
contribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel I should give the disclaimer that since the last time I talked
about how to contribute to Django, the Django folks added to their docs
a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/intro/contributing/"&gt;tutorial on how to make your first
contribution&lt;/a&gt;,
which just makes the project that little bit more awesome (and this
challenge, easier to solve!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-open-source-night-july"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next Open-Source Night: July&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So next month. That'll be on the 17th of July. Are you interested in
giving a talk? :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no one volunteers we'll have a session similar to the first event
except with more lightning talks. Lightning talks don't have to be
prepared, there's no need for slides or anything you don't fancy. It's
as simple as chatting about what you plan on doing or would like to do
during the evening, inviting others to join you if they'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hello, I'm Chris, a contributor to AwesomeProject which is a project
that does this and that and also that thing. At the moment we're looking
for help in $area1, $area2, $area41, if you think that's cool and you'd
like to help, I'll be sitting at that table over here, come and chat
with me. Maybe I can help you find a good first task. Otherwise I'll be
working on the defroglirnator for the project -- er if you have any
experience in that area I'd love to chat to you too.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or maybe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hey, I'm J. Bloggs, I've been using Wordpress for a few years, I think
it's an awesome project and I'd like to start giving back. Tonight my
plan is to figure out the new contributor process - if you're interested
too, we can do this together. Come and chat with me.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter if there is no existing contributor to the specific
project in the room. Since there are people familiar with the way
open-source projects and communities usually tick, they will be able to
help you if you get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, that's it! I'm hoping to also have the time to find a few good first
tasks in a new project, maybe
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.libreoffice.org/"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt;. If not, then we can
figure it out together on the day :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm very much looking forward to hearing your thoughts, suggestions and
ideas about all this, and perhaps also see you on the 17th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 20:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2013-07-02:/blog/2013/07/evolving-open-source-night/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>contributing</category><category>events</category><category>ireland</category><category>open-source</category><category>tog</category></item><item><title>Open-Source Night #2: March 2013</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2013/03/open-source-night-2-march-2013/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday the 20th, we had the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/03/open-source-night-2/"&gt;2nd edition of Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt; in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt;. I think it went well. Once again there was
about a dozen attendees, many of whom have never contributed to
open-source before. A third of them were also in Tog for the first time.
It might be too early to matter but there was also very little overlap
with the audience from last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="talks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the evening with 2 talks, meant to be about 15 minutes long
each. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogs.gnome.org/markmc/"&gt;Mark&lt;/a&gt; started the evening
telling us about open-source licences and the philosophy they
encapsulate/were born from. Then I walked through how one would go about
contributing to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;, basically
clicking through the Django website and explaining different tasks the
project needs help with, particularly for bug fixing contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we had 2 lightning talks that were meant to last 2 to 5
minutes, to give people a chance to talk about a project they contribute
to and get people to join in. This time the talks were more about ideas,
which is fine, but both also ran overtime, which is less cool. I'm not
sure if either found additional contributors/would-be contributors out
of it for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="hands-on"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hands-on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of the evening, the part that should be hands-on, didn't
go so well. After the talks (which lasted for 1h30 instead of 45mins)
and a tour of the hackerspace for the new people, most continued
chatting instead of sitting down and getting things done. This
especially saddened me for the ones who had never contributed before.
The goal of the event is to help newcomers get started contributing,
when they have experienced people at hand to ask questions to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-time"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure how to improve this next time and help attendees get
started actually doing stuff. Running overtime for the talks really hurt
for the rest of the evening, which is already such a short time to
accomplish something. An idea: after my talk I was asked &amp;quot;How long would
it take for someone to start from nothing to being able to run the
Django unit test suite?&amp;quot; and maybe this kind of well-defined,
self-contained task would be good to help people get started. It's not a
contribution yet, but it's a first, necessary step toward it (for code
contributions in any case), and it could be fun to try and mix this with
some sort of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openbadges.org"&gt;open badge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat related announcement: open-source night won't happen on April
17th next month but probably on April 24th instead. Check the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;tog.ie&lt;/a&gt; calendar for confirmation. If you're
interested in speaking on a topic relating to the life of open-source or
a project in particular, please get in touch :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 20:22:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2013-03-24:/blog/2013/03/open-source-night-2-march-2013/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>contributing</category><category>django</category><category>events</category><category>ireland</category><category>open-source</category><category>tog</category></item></channel></rss>