<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jpichon.net - contributing</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/feeds/tag-contributing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jpichon.net/</id><updated>2017-02-27T21:42:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>FOSDEM 2017 | From the community devroom</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2017/02/fosdem-2017-event-report/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-27T21:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-27T21:42:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2017-02-27:/blog/2017/02/fosdem-2017-event-report/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I happily went off to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;.
Saturday I caught up with people, Sunday I spent most of the day in the
incredibly busy &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/track/community/"&gt;Community
devroom&lt;/a&gt; - right
until I had to give up my seat for food. I really enjoyed the talks and
hope the track manages …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I happily went off to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;.
Saturday I caught up with people, Sunday I spent most of the day in the
incredibly busy &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/track/community/"&gt;Community
devroom&lt;/a&gt; - right
until I had to give up my seat for food. I really enjoyed the talks and
hope the track manages to get a bigger devroom next year, dozens of
people had to be kept out after every session ended (fire safety
regulations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most talks lasted about 30mn and the videos should be available on the
FOSDEM website. Here are some of the highlights from my perspective and
notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="closing-loops-greg-sutcliffe"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing Loops (Greg Sutcliffe)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_closing_loops/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was more about raising questions and figuring out best
practices based on audience participation rather than offering The One
Solution. In this context, a &amp;quot;loop&amp;quot; means an RFC still undecided, a
discussion dying out, patches unreviewed. How do you decide when a topic
has come to a conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to remember that everybody has the best interests of the
project at heart, this is more about blaming the systems we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say, in a Request For Comments discussing significant changes on a
mailing list, the discussion tends to peter out after a while, and it
can be difficult to track how a proposal evolved. Foreman (Greg's
project) decided to move the discussions to an RFC repository instead,
but 6 months later it seems to have only moved the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the audience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For Debian, the discussion ends &amp;quot;when someone starts the work&amp;quot; :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LibreOffice has a &amp;quot;technical council&amp;quot; type meeting/discussion with
about 40 people, on the phone. A wiki documents the process to join.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the PHP world, the RFC author gets to choose when to call a vote
and the deadline for it (at least 2 weeks ahead). Greg wondered if
that might get divisive if there are too many 50/50 situations, but
the audience member indicated that it wasn't the case, because most
problems get solved during the discussions that precede the vote so
they are usually overwhelmingly accepted. Every contributor gets a
vote from a certain contribution threshold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker seemed interested in trying out the technical council
direction for his project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="data-science-for-community-management-manrique-lopez"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data science for community management (Manrique Lopez)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_datascience_for_communitymanagement/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communities need to have a common vision and self-awareness to see if
they are walking toward it: what kind of people are part of the
community, what are they doing... This helps with governance and
transparency (fairness, trust).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the role of a community manager? Do communities even need to be
managed? &amp;quot;Manage&amp;quot; is a strong word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A community manager is interested in keeping their community alive,
active, and productive. Having visibility into community health is
important. There are a lot of tools out there with data relevant to
this: JIRA, git, IRC, slack, StackOverflow, ... A lot of places, which
individually are only one part of the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than cobling a bunch of scripts together to get to all that data,
GrimoireLab does all the work for you and presents it nicely using
graphs. One example was the &amp;quot;Pony Factor,&amp;quot; which I hadn't heard of:
who's doing 50% of the commits? For example in the kernel, the pony
factor is about 200 people/10 companies. That's a lot of people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have that data you can see the evolution of the project over
time: reviews, gender, demography, pony factor, etc, etc. Cauldron.io,
in beta, lets you try it out for free for up to 5 Github organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="getting-your-issues-fixed-tomer-brisker"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting your issues fixed (Tomer Brisker)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_getting_your_issues_fixed/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think anyone trying to get help or start contributing as a user to an
open-source project needs to watch this. Tomer summarised a ton of best
practices that experienced open-source people &amp;quot;just know&amp;quot; and would
likely never think to document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A super rough summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to ask for help on IRC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try the mailing list. If no one replies and you solve it yourself or
find a workaround later, please self-reply. (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://xkcd.com/979/"&gt;Mandatory xkcd
link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search the bug tracker. If there is a bug, add your input, your use
case. If there are none, create a new issue and include as much
information as possible: traces, logs, version (including of the
plugin if relevant), screenshots... Anything to help the developers
reproduce the issue. If this is a feature request, explain your use
case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tabs vs spaces: follow the coding guidelines for the project. If
there aren't any follow the standards and conventions of the existing
code base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the commit message good. Explain &amp;quot;why&amp;quot; as completely as
possible. Apparently Github even lets you include screenshots, so
that the patch can be reviewed without having to pull the code. &amp;quot;Why&amp;quot;
did you do it this way and not another way, explained in such a way
people in the future can understand the decision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include tests. This protects against regressions, so that you don't
have to fix the same bug two releases later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be kind. We're building a community. No one wants to be shouted at.
Be patient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="handle-conflict-like-a-boss-deb-nicholson"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Handle conflict, like a boss! (Deb Nicholson)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_handle_conflict_like_a_boss/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conflicts often come from a piece of information that is missing.
Conflict is natural. If you don't handle it, it will come back worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we minimise it? Try to understand the other people, where they're
coming from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passion. When people get so excited about something they forget why
they're doing it. Mismatched goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity. When someone's identity is linked to a task, not a goal.
For example, the person known to be super helpful with wrangling the
complex bug tracker, who'll end up sad when you finally upgrade to
something better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't leave conflict unattended or you'll end up in a snake pit. You
don't owe your mental health to any FOSS project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 3 styles of handling conflict. We tend to use them all,
depending on the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoidance. This is not good in a project! It festers. It looks like
you don't care, like you're not connected to the community and its
concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accommodation. Doing stuff you don't really want to in order to keep
the group happy. For bigger issues it can make it look like you don't
mind the way things are going. It works for small things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assertion. Can also be called Aggression. Name calling, etc. Not a
good strategy. It wears out other contributors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversations happen in many places. Document the decisions so that it
doesn't feel like they're coming out of nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you notice in passing a problem in the community you're probably
missing some information. Gather more info in order to understand the
source of conflict: misunderstanding goals, stepping on toes (e.g. that
person &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; writes the release notes but someone else went ahead and
did it this time instead, without asking), ... Is it new members
clashing with the old ones? Go back to the historical vision, step out
of the tactical discussion. Are there sekrit goals underway? For example
a motivation you're not aware of, someone with different goals for their
participation like a new job or internal deadlines...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the conflict is based on fear, it can be harder to get at, e.g.
someone afraid they can't learn a new skill if switching language.
Create a back channel where it's safe to discuss, to try to deal with
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planning for future conflict:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assume the best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a code of conduct. Set expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No name calling/ad hominem, only discuss technical merits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set an example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could do so much more in the FOSS world if we didn't spend so much
time slagging each other :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some references:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17568812-everything-is-workable"&gt;Everything is
workable&lt;/a&gt;
- Diana Musko Hamilton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.aurynn.com/contempt-culture"&gt;Contempt Culture&lt;/a&gt; -
Aurynn Shaw.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mentoring-101-brian-proffitt"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mentoring 101 (Brian Proffitt)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_mentoring_101/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a lively talk on both formal mentoring via programs such as
the&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; as
well as daily mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onboarding is important. This is not just about keeping people in but
helping people get in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As software project, should you want to participate in formal mentoring:
have a plan. Formal programs have their own rules and structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a participant, be a member of the community, pick a project that
interests you. Be ready to commit. Be flexible - it takes time but is
rewarding. Be ready to ask for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Undermentoring&lt;/em&gt; is a problem. Have clear, set goals for the mentee.
Keep an eye on them while also giving them space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Issue with mentees disappearing... They really should keep a line of
communication open, even if only to say, &amp;quot;sorry, I cant' participate
anymore.&amp;quot; (From personal experience mentoring, this is quite stressful
and it was a relief when the mentee admitted they could no longer
participate.) You need to proactively mentor to avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be consistent. E.g. your style may be authoritative (do it this way),
democratic (collaboration) or coaching (guidance). Stick to one.
(...with Brian noting that the last one is best for mentoring!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set expectations. Make sure the goals are aligned, define the
process, avoid confusion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take an interest in the mentee. Listen actively. Build a
relationship. Learn their style. Don't be a stalker though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait before giving advice. It's easy to try to fix things when
someone comes at you with a problem. You might be able to solve it
but that won't help them. Hit the pause button. Ask more question,
get to the heart, guide them to the solution. It takes time. You may
not solve the problem. As long as it's not time-sensitive that's ok.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't assume anything. Avoid stereotypes. Learn the details of a
situation. Emphasise communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember this one thing: they aren't you!! Understand the mentee. This
is not only about getting the project done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A question from the audience was, how can I help my mentor as a mentee?
Once again it's about being proactive: this is what I want to do, how do
you help me do this? If it isn't working, reconsider the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to recruit mentors? Some projects are easier to get in than others.
In oVirt, there's a separate mailing list and no formal process. Spread
the word, see who's interested. What about a project where there's a lot
of mentees yet no one ever answers the call for mentors? If this is part
of a corporate project, a solution could be to make it part of the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="impromptu-community-talk"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impromptu community talk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the talks was cancelled, so a couple of people started a
conversation around community and community events (too many pizzas, too
much alcohol is the feedback I remember from that part).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for &amp;quot;cruel empathy&amp;quot; was brought up: sometimes meeting
organisers should be jerks for good reasons. Loud, demeaning people are
toxic and need to be called out. Tell them, in private: &amp;quot;I appreciate
that you're here, etc, but you're sucking air out of the community.&amp;quot;
They may not realise they are doing it, so be nice about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shotwell community was brought up as one with great first contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="overcoming-culture-clash-dave-neary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overcoming culture clash (Dave Neary)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_overcoming_culture_clash/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a very interesting talk, mainly summarising information and
graphs from books, which I'm going to list here. And hopefully read
soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically a lot of what we do and how we interpret things depends on our
upbringing (country, culture, ...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.garretthardinsociety.org/articles_pdf/tragedy_of_the_commons.pdf"&gt;The Tragedy of the
Commons&lt;/a&gt;
- Garret Hardin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17707599-moral-tribes"&gt;Moral
Tribes&lt;/a&gt;
- Joshua Greene.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/466760.Cultures_and_Organizations"&gt;Culture and
Organizations&lt;/a&gt;
- Geert Hofstede. That one brings up 6 dimensions of culture, for
example tending to be uncomfortable with silence and filling it
instantly, vs. leaving a couple seconds pause to make sure the person
is finished.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/313605.Getting_to_Yes"&gt;Getting to
Yes&lt;/a&gt; -
Roger Fish. This is more psychology-based than about hard
negotiation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no easy solutions. Focus on the relationship. Take small
steps: one conversation at a time. Encourage local user groups - though
keep them connected e.g. via sending mentors/leaders to these meetups to
avoid silos. Have short mentoring programs. Learn about the cultural
norms and sensitivity of the community. Avoid real-time meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="i-contributed-but-what-now-bee-padalkar"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I contributed! But what now? (Bee Padalkar)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fosdem.org/2017/schedule/event/community_contributed_now_what/"&gt;Link to
talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the Fedora community, this talk was about improving contributor
retention rates by finding patterns about successful contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do people &lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt;? According to a survey they ran, usually thanks to
the strong, positive and inclusive community. Other reasons were
identifying with the Fedora foundations (core values), giving back,
constantly learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how interesting the project is, if the community is poor
people don't stick around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a defined onboarding process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage people to speak up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign action items early on, to create a sense of responsibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let people know they are doing good work, give feedback (e.g. IRC
karma).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use inclusive and motivating language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage attending events to meet people in person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage consistency over activity. Let people contribute according
to their own time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspire, interact, give feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help people identify with your mission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to next year's event!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="fosdem"></category><category term="open-source"></category></entry><entry><title>Training at EuroPython 2014 | Making your first contribution to OpenStack</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2014/08/training-europython-2014/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-08-01T11:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-08-01T11:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2014-08-01:/blog/2014/08/training-europython-2014/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenStack logo" src="http://www.openstack.org/assets/openstack-logo/openstack-cloud-software-vertical-small.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I ran a 3-hour training on how to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ep2014.europython.eu/en/schedule/sessions/76/"&gt;get started contributing to
OpenStack&lt;/a&gt; at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ep2014.europython.eu/en/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt;. The aim was to give a
high-level overview of how the contribution process works in the project
and guide people through making their first contribution, from account
creation to submitting a patch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="overview"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview …&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OpenStack logo" src="http://www.openstack.org/assets/openstack-logo/openstack-cloud-software-vertical-small.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I ran a 3-hour training on how to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ep2014.europython.eu/en/schedule/sessions/76/"&gt;get started contributing to
OpenStack&lt;/a&gt; at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ep2014.europython.eu/en/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt;. The aim was to give a
high-level overview of how the contribution process works in the project
and guide people through making their first contribution, from account
creation to submitting a patch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="overview"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session starts with an extremely fast overview of OpenStack, geared
toward giving the participants an idea of the different components and
possible areas for contribution. We then go through creating the
accounts, why they're all needed, and how to work with DevStack for the
people who have installed it. From there we finally start talking about
the contribution process itself, some general points on open-source and
OpenStack culture then go through a number of ideas for small tasks
suitable for a first contribution. After that it's down to the
participants to work on something and prepare a patch. Some people chose
to file and triage/confirm bugs. The last part is about making sure the
patch matches the community standards, submitting it, and talking about
what happens next both to the patch and to the participant as a new
member of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="preparing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the weeks preceding the event, I ran two pilot workshops with
small groups (less than 10 people) in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/"&gt;my local
hackerspace&lt;/a&gt;, in preparation for the big one in
Berlin. That was absolutely invaluable in terms of making the material
more understandable and refining the content for items I didn't think of
covering initially (e.g. screen, openrc files) and topics that could use
more in-depth explanations (e.g. how to find your first task), timings,
and generally getting a feel for what's reasonably achievable within a
3-hour intro workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="delivering"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Delivering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it went well, despite some issues at the beginning due to lack
of Internet connectivity (always a problem during hands-on workshops!).
About 70 people had signed up to attend (a.k.a. about 7 times too many),
thankfully other members of the OpenStack community stepped up and
offered their help as mentors - thanks again everyone! In the end, about
half the participants showed up in the morning, and we lost another
dozen to the Internet woes. The people who stayed were mostly
enthusiastic and seemed happy with the experience. According to the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/ep-openstack"&gt;session etherpad&lt;/a&gt;, at
least 5 new contributors uploaded a first patch :) Three are merged so
far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributing the slides early proved popular and useful. For an
interactive workshop with lots of links and references it's really
helpful for people to go back on something they missed or want to check
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="issues"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start of the workshop is a bit lecture-heavy and could be titled
&amp;quot;Things I Desperately Wish I Knew When Starting Out,&amp;quot; and although
there's some quizzes/discussions/demoing I'd love to make it more
interactive in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information requested in order to join the Foundation tends to
surprise people, I think because people come at it from the perspective
of &amp;quot;I want to submit a patch&amp;quot; rather than &amp;quot;I am preparing to join a
Foundation.&amp;quot; At the hackerspace sessions in particular (maybe because it
was easier to have candid discussions in such a small group), people
weren't impressed with being forced to state an affiliation. The lack of
obvious answer for volunteers gave the impression that the project cares
more about contributions from companies. &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
might make an appearance in the company stats in the future :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the sign-up form, the &amp;quot;Statement of Interest&amp;quot; is intimidating and
confusing for some people (I certainly remember being uncertain over
mine and what was appropriate, back when I was new and joining the
Foundation was optional!). I worked around this after the initial
session by offering suggestions/tips for both these fields, and spoke a
bit more about their purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few people suggested I simply tell people to sign up for all these
accounts in advance so there's more time during the workshop to work on
the contribution itself. It's an option, though a number of people still
hit non-obvious issues with Gerrit that are difficult to debug (some we
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/openstack-ci/+bug/1346833"&gt;opened bugs&lt;/a&gt;
for, others we added to the etherpad). During one of the pilot sessions
at the hackerspace, 6 of the 7 participants had errors when running git
review -s&amp;nbsp; - I'm still not sure why, as it Worked On My Machine (tm)
just fine at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I'm glad I did this! It was interesting to extract all this
information from my brain, wiki pages and docs and attempt to make it as
consumable as possible. It's really exciting when people come back later
to say they've made a contribution and that the session helped to make
the process less scary and more comprehensible. Thanks to all the
participants who took the time to offer feedback as well! I hope I can
continue to improve on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="europython"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="openstack"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolving Open-Source Night | Open-Source Night - June</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2013/07/evolving-open-source-night/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-02T20:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-07-02T20:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2013-07-02:/blog/2013/07/evolving-open-source-night/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The monthly Open-Source night experiment continues. On Wednesday, June
19th we had the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/06/open-source-night-june/"&gt;June edition of Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.technomancy.org/"&gt;Rory&lt;/a&gt; gave us a
slightly-longer-than-15-minutes talk on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openstreetmap.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, and the kind of
contributions the project welcomes (data data data, really!). I was the
only one to volunteer for a lightning talk, in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The monthly Open-Source night experiment continues. On Wednesday, June
19th we had the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/06/open-source-night-june/"&gt;June edition of Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.technomancy.org/"&gt;Rory&lt;/a&gt; gave us a
slightly-longer-than-15-minutes talk on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openstreetmap.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, and the kind of
contributions the project welcomes (data data data, really!). I was the
only one to volunteer for a lightning talk, in stark contrast with the
last event where we had multiple ones both by people attending
open-source night and network people who happened to be visiting the
hackerspace at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than doing an on-topic talk about an open-source project, I did a
meta-talk about Open-Source Night itself and different ways in which it
could evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I make no secret that I don't think open-source night works very well in
its current format. My goal (and measure for success) is to help people
actually get started contributing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: if you were at my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedotconf.wordpress.com/whos-speaking/julie-pichon/"&gt;deep dive on contributing to
open-source&lt;/a&gt;
and planning on attending the next open-source night, please do come!!
This all just means that I think there are things that can be improved
:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reminder-the-current-format"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reminder: The current format&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're currently meeting on the 3rd Wednesday of the month. The event
usually starts with two 15 minutes talk, ideally one on the life of
open-source (e.g. licences, version control, IRC, using the
command-line...) and one on how to contribute to a specific project.
Then there's a number of 5-minutes-long-or-less lightning talks where
people can introduce the project they will be working on during the
evening. Then people break into groups or independently work on an
open-source project of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or that's the idea anyway. The talks usually work well and are
inspiring, though they tend to run overtime and then people have trouble
sitting at a table and doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are my thoughts and ideas as to where open-source night might go
in the future. These are not plans. I would like to hear feedback from
interested people - attendees, would-be attendees, other organisers and
thoughtful passerbys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="topics-general-open-source-vs-project-specific"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics: General open-source vs Project-specific&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see value in both topics, but perhaps attendees and would-be attendees
favour one or the other, both, or neither? I haven't really heard much
on this, what people find most useful. I think the project specific
talks at least are interesting for both newcomers and established
contributors, to see how other projects do things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe 15 minutes is a good amount of time to get an overview, get
inspired and get ideas. And not get too bored if already familiar with
the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could see the value and how efficient it would be to focus on one
project for a full session and guide people through contributing to it.
However I can also see how it could be offputting to people not
particularly interested in the project (e.g. &amp;quot;I don't use that distro,
why should I bother attending?&amp;quot;). Perhaps as separate, off-shoot events
if people are interested in leading that kind of session (get in
touch!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="topics-all-kind-of-contributions-vs-focusing-on-code"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics: All kind of contributions vs Focusing on code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, I try really hard to emphasise (and encourage speakers to
do the same) all the kinds of contributions that can be made - and are
well needed! - even though my own experience lies in code-based
contributions. Maybe I should give up on being inclusive and focus on
what I know best, rather than try to be all things to all people?
Code-focused open-source events could go from learning to program to
fixing a bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I was hoping people would step up to talk and encourage people
to join their area of interest (I think we have e.g. experienced
open-source translators around...) but that hasn't happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually a point where someone came up to me after the talk and
said straight off they really liked the breadth of contributions demoed
during the talks, in particular mentioning &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/05/open-source-night-may/"&gt;last month's
talk&lt;/a&gt; by Guilherme
on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openmandriva.org"&gt;OpenMandriva&lt;/a&gt; that did a great job
showing how someone can help, in a multitude of ways, even if they're
not all that confident in their coding skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="format-more-course-like"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Format: More course-like?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of days before the June OSS Night I was pointed to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://opensource.com/life/13/6/learning-program-open-source-way"&gt;this
article on a really, really interesting summer course on learning to
program the open-source
way&lt;/a&gt;.
That's a really cool concept. Should we entertain the thought of doing
something similar during open-source night? e.g. A session on learning
how to use version control with exercises, very workshop like, one
month, some other topic the next one, etc.?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not, but something to consider as a separate course with a
shorter timeline. A course with one session a month will lose people and
have little momentum. Is this the kind of things people have an interest
in learning?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="format-doing-vs-listening-talking"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Format: Doing vs Listening/Talking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal with this event is still to get people started contributing. I'm
not interested in organising a monthly night of talks. Finding speakers
is stressful. If the talks aren't followed by some contributing action,
to me the event is failing and I'm not interested in continuing to
organise it. There are plenty of events around Dublin already where
people can meet, talk tech and shoot the breeze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regard to open-source related talks, I think that's already handled
well by the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.linux.ie"&gt;ILUG&lt;/a&gt; folks, who are now keen to
set them up regularly again under the new chairmanship :) And we can
join forces if that's the most attractive part of the event to folks. If
your main interest is in having a regular night of open-source talks,
get in touch and I'll be happy to help you have this in Tog. I'd attend
with pleasure anyway, I'm just not interested in organising it and go
speaker-hunting every 3 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still believe we can make something really cool happen by putting in
the same room people experienced in open-source together with newcomers
interested in contributing. So I'm not giving up yet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's of course also the timeframe issue: with or without talks, an
evening of maybe 3 hours is not a lot of time to accomplish something.
Maybe we could (also/instead?) have events on Saturdays? And/or week-end
workshops, Friday eve to Sunday?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOWEVER, in any case an evening is still enough time to accomplish
&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, get started, get the momentum going, get unblocked and
finish your contribution later at the week-end, in your own time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="you-why-are-you-here-anyway"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;You: Why are you here anyway*? ;)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* Or why weren't you? :) I'm just as interested in the answer to that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in learning how to contribute? Interested in helping
and mentoring newcomers? What were you hoping this evening would be
about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then invited people to have a productive discussion with me about this
should they wish to, somewhat contradicting my own doing vs talking rant
:-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free and welcome to continue the discussion in the comments
or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/about/"&gt;by email&lt;/a&gt;, I would love to pick
more brains and exchange ideas about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="django-challenge"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Django challenge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid the talk being entirely meta (and in case people didn't care
that much about all the blah blah blah and more about the doing!), I
issued a challenge to attendees as well: this evening, run the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; unit tests suite. If that's
something you're set up for, it'll take 2 minutes. If you're familiar
with the concept but don't have all the dependencies set up yet it'll
take 20 minutes. If this is all new to you it might take 2 hours, but
what you learn you'll be able to reuse when you start working on a
project you care about in the future, and it means it'll take less long
then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person took me up on it and it took them 10 minutes. This shows how
possible it is to actually get the ball rolling during open-source
night, get people to realise they're not that far away from a first
contribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel I should give the disclaimer that since the last time I talked
about how to contribute to Django, the Django folks added to their docs
a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/intro/contributing/"&gt;tutorial on how to make your first
contribution&lt;/a&gt;,
which just makes the project that little bit more awesome (and this
challenge, easier to solve!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-open-source-night-july"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next Open-Source Night: July&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So next month. That'll be on the 17th of July. Are you interested in
giving a talk? :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no one volunteers we'll have a session similar to the first event
except with more lightning talks. Lightning talks don't have to be
prepared, there's no need for slides or anything you don't fancy. It's
as simple as chatting about what you plan on doing or would like to do
during the evening, inviting others to join you if they'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hello, I'm Chris, a contributor to AwesomeProject which is a project
that does this and that and also that thing. At the moment we're looking
for help in $area1, $area2, $area41, if you think that's cool and you'd
like to help, I'll be sitting at that table over here, come and chat
with me. Maybe I can help you find a good first task. Otherwise I'll be
working on the defroglirnator for the project -- er if you have any
experience in that area I'd love to chat to you too.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or maybe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hey, I'm J. Bloggs, I've been using Wordpress for a few years, I think
it's an awesome project and I'd like to start giving back. Tonight my
plan is to figure out the new contributor process - if you're interested
too, we can do this together. Come and chat with me.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter if there is no existing contributor to the specific
project in the room. Since there are people familiar with the way
open-source projects and communities usually tick, they will be able to
help you if you get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, that's it! I'm hoping to also have the time to find a few good first
tasks in a new project, maybe
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.libreoffice.org/"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt;. If not, then we can
figure it out together on the day :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm very much looking forward to hearing your thoughts, suggestions and
ideas about all this, and perhaps also see you on the 17th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="ireland"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry><entry><title>Open-Source Night #2: March 2013</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2013/03/open-source-night-2-march-2013/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-24T20:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-03-24T20:22:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2013-03-24:/blog/2013/03/open-source-night-2-march-2013/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday the 20th, we had the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/03/open-source-night-2/"&gt;2nd edition of Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt; in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt;. I think it went well. Once again there was
about a dozen attendees, many of whom have never contributed to
open-source before. A third of them were also in Tog for the first time.
It might …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday the 20th, we had the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/03/open-source-night-2/"&gt;2nd edition of Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt; in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt;. I think it went well. Once again there was
about a dozen attendees, many of whom have never contributed to
open-source before. A third of them were also in Tog for the first time.
It might be too early to matter but there was also very little overlap
with the audience from last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="talks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the evening with 2 talks, meant to be about 15 minutes long
each. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogs.gnome.org/markmc/"&gt;Mark&lt;/a&gt; started the evening
telling us about open-source licences and the philosophy they
encapsulate/were born from. Then I walked through how one would go about
contributing to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;, basically
clicking through the Django website and explaining different tasks the
project needs help with, particularly for bug fixing contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we had 2 lightning talks that were meant to last 2 to 5
minutes, to give people a chance to talk about a project they contribute
to and get people to join in. This time the talks were more about ideas,
which is fine, but both also ran overtime, which is less cool. I'm not
sure if either found additional contributors/would-be contributors out
of it for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="hands-on"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hands-on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of the evening, the part that should be hands-on, didn't
go so well. After the talks (which lasted for 1h30 instead of 45mins)
and a tour of the hackerspace for the new people, most continued
chatting instead of sitting down and getting things done. This
especially saddened me for the ones who had never contributed before.
The goal of the event is to help newcomers get started contributing,
when they have experienced people at hand to ask questions to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-time"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure how to improve this next time and help attendees get
started actually doing stuff. Running overtime for the talks really hurt
for the rest of the evening, which is already such a short time to
accomplish something. An idea: after my talk I was asked &amp;quot;How long would
it take for someone to start from nothing to being able to run the
Django unit test suite?&amp;quot; and maybe this kind of well-defined,
self-contained task would be good to help people get started. It's not a
contribution yet, but it's a first, necessary step toward it (for code
contributions in any case), and it could be fun to try and mix this with
some sort of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openbadges.org"&gt;open badge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat related announcement: open-source night won't happen on April
17th next month but probably on April 24th instead. Check the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;tog.ie&lt;/a&gt; calendar for confirmation. If you're
interested in speaking on a topic relating to the life of open-source or
a project in particular, please get in touch :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="django"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="ireland"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry><entry><title>Open-Source Night: Event #1 | February 20th</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2013/02/open-source-night-event-1/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-23T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-02-23T08:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2013-02-23:/blog/2013/02/open-source-night-event-1/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt; hosted the first monthly
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/01/one-small-step-open-source-night/"&gt;Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an event I'd been wanting to organise for a while, with an eye on
it being hands-on and slanted toward helping interested people get
started in open-source, but I wasn't sure what format would work best.
I'm still not sure …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt; hosted the first monthly
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2013/01/one-small-step-open-source-night/"&gt;Open-Source
Night&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an event I'd been wanting to organise for a while, with an eye on
it being hands-on and slanted toward helping interested people get
started in open-source, but I wasn't sure what format would work best.
I'm still not sure, but in the spirit of release early, release often, I
thought I'd give it a shot for a few months and iterate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first event, about a dozen people showed up. About 7-9 of them
had already made some kind of contribution, most people had a clear idea
of the project they wanted to contribute to for the evening, and 3 were
hesitant and not sure what they wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2013/opensourcenight_blackboard.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Blackboard with project names" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2013/opensourcenight_blackboard-small.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started with 2 super short talks, an ill-prepared one from myself
about what to do tonight: basically find the contributor's guidelines
for the project you're interested in and speak to the person next to you
for help, since we had such a skewed ratio of experienced contributors.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scienceisdelicious.com/"&gt;Triona&lt;/a&gt; followed with a talk on what
she planned to do in the evening with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://free-penguin.org/"&gt;Free
Penguin&lt;/a&gt;, an open-source sewing pattern for
Tux plushes. The maintainer hasn't updated nor responded to emails in
years, so it seems it will need to be forked in order to start improving
the documentation. Open-source projects aren't all about code! :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I directed the hesitant project-less people toward
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chebe.dreamwidth.org/"&gt;Cheryl&lt;/a&gt; and the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dreamwidth.org/"&gt;Dreamwidth&lt;/a&gt; project, which has an
excellent reputation for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.linuxplanet.com/linuxplanet/reports/6939/1"&gt;being friendly to
newcomers&lt;/a&gt;.
Even without an experienced contributor around, I thought figuring
things out together would be a fun learning experience. It may not have
been that effective though, people were interested and looked around but
nothing got accomplished (perhaps that is to be expected for a first
couple of hours getting acquainted with a project and open-source?).
Then further efforts were thwarted by technical problems (bugzilla
down). Cheryl's thoughts abut this is that it's difficult to get into a
project one doesn't feel strongly about (a similar downside applies to
projects discovered via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://openhatch.org"&gt;OpenHatch&lt;/a&gt;, as someone
else mentioned to me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a couple of serendipitous meetings, like the person wanting
to get started with Debian packaging who happened to be sitting besides
a Debian Developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But overall, I think having encouraged people to come along already
having a project in mind made it difficult to form groups and encourage
collaboration, because people ended up working on the project they had
planned to alone. It may not have been a great experience, particularly
for people who didn't know anyone or hadn't been in Tog before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also need to become more familiar with projects who have good,
specific non-programming-related tasks for newcomers. I had a general
idea but wasted time trying to find the details. We had a graphic
designer interested in either contributing his design skills,
translating or participating in testing efforts but I wasn't able to
quickly find a good &amp;quot;Here's a concrete task you can do now&amp;quot; for some of
the better known projects. He did discover InkScape and became eager to
learn it, so I hope to see him again in Tog in a few weeks for teaching
an intro workshop to InkScape :-) (Thanks Borud!!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ideas-on-how-to-evolve-the-format-for-next-time"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ideas on how to evolve the format for next time:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose one project and make it the main focus of the evening, at least
at the start. Meaning only one presentation, that is a bit longer
(ideally 20 minutes, max 30 -- we still need time to actually do stuff!)
and give specific, step-by-step instructions on &amp;quot;this is where you go to
find something to work on, this is how you choose a task&amp;quot; and afterwards
have the people interested in working on the project do so together -
several people to one task can work, to encourage learning together and
avoid getting stuck. People are still welcome to work on whatever else
they want to of course. This was suggested by
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://spamt.net/"&gt;Ulrich&lt;/a&gt; based on the recent Debian Bug Squashing
Parties he attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://eirebecky.wordpress.com/"&gt;Becky&lt;/a&gt; said there was an interest
in a GitHub pair programming type of exercise. People upload code on
GitHub they never touch again. Working on someone else's code with the
help of the author could turn into an instructive experience. It would
also be cool to see what a pull request looks like from both sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we can try both these things for next time, the GitHub pair
programming could start after the presentation for people not interested
in working on the highlighted project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now. The next step is to find a project to highlight and a willing
contributor who'd like to present and guide, for the next session on
March 20th. Ideas, volunteers? :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback and general thoughts on evolving the format are warmly welcome
as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="ireland"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry></feed>