<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jpichon.net - education</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/feeds/tag-education.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jpichon.net/</id><updated>2012-02-29T20:06:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>CESI 2012 | "TEACHnology: Merging teaching and technology in schools"</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2012/02/cesi-2012/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-02-29T20:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-02-29T20:06:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2012-02-29:/blog/2012/02/cesi-2012/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday I attended &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://cesi.ie/conference-2012"&gt;CESI 2012&lt;/a&gt;,
a conference organised by the Computers in Education Society of Ireland.
It's a conference aimed at teachers and this was the first time I
attended. Even though as an IT professional I wasn't really the target
audience, I really enjoyed the talks and left …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday I attended &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://cesi.ie/conference-2012"&gt;CESI 2012&lt;/a&gt;,
a conference organised by the Computers in Education Society of Ireland.
It's a conference aimed at teachers and this was the first time I
attended. Even though as an IT professional I wasn't really the target
audience, I really enjoyed the talks and left the day with my head full
of ideas and really happy with the interesting conversations I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random highlights and talk summaries from the day...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="opening-talks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opening talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the opening talks, Gerard McHugh told us that the lack of
engaging content explains failing western schools. Even though many
things in life have become more engaging over the decades, school
hasn't: we need it to be more interactive, more collaborative and
encourage participatory active learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the keynote, Stephen Howell animately encouraged school teachers to
do the PR for third-level courses :-) and help students find that spark
to discover if they would enjoy a career in IT. The &amp;quot;3 Ds&amp;quot; should be
taught in school: Design, Develop and Debug -- not all of them require
computers or knowing how to code. Using software such as
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scratch.mit.edu/"&gt;Scratch&lt;/a&gt;, students can be moved to a
producer role as opposed to what they do with most wonderful modern
devices such as the iPad or xBox, that are slanted toward consuming
content. The goal is to get them to make their own games. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scratch.saorog.com/"&gt;Scratch +
Kinect&lt;/a&gt; demo was quite impressive :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-brief-history-of-the-near-future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A brief history of the near future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Hefferman looked at what technologies are currently being created,
citing an interesting quote: &amp;quot;The future is already there, it's just not
evenly distributed.&amp;quot; If we look at what R&amp;amp;D departments are working on
right now, there will be less of a surprise when it arrives into the
classroom in 10 or 20 years. &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wp.nmc.org/horizon2011/"&gt;The Horizon
Report&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; relates technological
innovations that are coming up. John ended the talk by telling us
examples of how all this will affect history teaching and the classroom
in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the questions was about how to bring some of the tools to the
classroom, when there are school and curriculum constraints. The answer
was that it's better to ask for forgiveness that permission, and start
under the radar initially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="game-based-learning-in-irish-education"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Game-based learning in Irish education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patrick Felicia is doing research on the impact of games in education.
His surveys indicate that most teachers agree games are a good learning
tool, that improves plenty of skills (with a bit of hesitation regarding
social skills, which is likely due to people having different types of
game in mind). However despite agreeing on the benefits, only a tiny
percentage have actually used any in their classroom. Most of the talk
took the form of a conversation with the audience, aiming to figure out
why this is and people's thoughts about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problems and constraints strongly relate to the curriculum and
time constraints. There is not a lot of content tailored for the Irish
market. Teachers suggested a portal of suitable games, and bringing
workshops on how to use them to the schools to make sure people attend
and learn about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone suggested, inspired by Stephen Howell's keynote, to have
children develop the content :-) This way they get to use their
creativity, meaningful content is created and they are taking
responsibility for it. Teach to create!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wit.ie/Research/ResearchGroupsCentres/Groups/GameBasedLearning//igbl2011/"&gt;iGBL&lt;/a&gt;
is an Irish conference on game-based learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-livescribe-pen-in-action"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The LiveScribe pen in action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adrienne Webb explained to us what the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.livescribe.com"&gt;LiveScribe
pen&lt;/a&gt; is, how it can be used and how she
uses it to provide additional resources to her students. The pen is a
very interesting piece of technology that records what you're writing
and your voice, which you can then upload or send as a video. There are
cool additional little features, such as clicking an element of the
video to listen to the playback of what was said when that particular
element was drawn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She used it to provide sample exam answers, so the students can focus on
what they want and ask questions only on what they are having difficulty
with. This worked better and more efficiently that trying to cover every
question for everyone over 40 minutes. The students - in an exam year -
really took to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="social-networking-with-our-students"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Social networking with our students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slideshare.net/cicronin/cesi12-digital-identity-privacy-authenticity"&gt;Catherine
Cronin&lt;/a&gt;
related her very interesting experience on using social media such as
Twitter and Google Plus to interact with students for a third-level
module, touching on themes such as digital identity, privacy and
authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently there is a tension between the current model of delivering
education, standardised, static and stale versus a student-centred
model. Meaningful learning occurs with knowledge construction, not
knowledge reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 5 stages to go through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness (of what is going on)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commitment (which requires time and learning)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access (to the appropriate technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authority (to change things, which is easier at the 3rd level since
you can do what you want for the modules you teach)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is about challenging students while still honouring who they are
and how they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Google Plus experiment was leaky (in that G+ makes it easy to
re-share stuff that was submitted privately to a circle), though this
accidentally made the conversation more authentic by allowing the author
of a book they were studying, Jeff Jarvis, to join in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is of course a dilemma between being graded and having an
authentic discussion. From the student's point of view, there was a wide
spectrum of opinions with regard to the usefulness of social networks,
thoughts on privacy and comfort expressing opinions in public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Student comments covered a wide range in terms of appreciation of the
experiment. The general opinion seems to be that it was useful, but/and
messy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk Q&amp;amp;A reflected on the dangers of having students participate in
that kind of public discussions, at a stage where they're likely still
trying on different identities to find themselves. This is going to
happen anyway, so it might as well be within the context of a class with
someone to offer guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="moodle-in-the-classroom"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moodle in the classroom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Declan Donnelly gave a nice introduction to Moodle by explaining to us
how his primary school uses it -- all of which is also applicable to the
secondary level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation mainly focused on the possibilities offered by
interactive exercises, notably by linking with SCORM compatible software
like Hot Potatoes, which is better than the basic Moodle quizzes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Moodle it's easier to share resources and do grading and
assessment. It acts as a digital link between home and school, both to
do the work (including drafts) and show off accomplishments to the
family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This link also applies to staff, as the school they use Moodle to
publish policies and meeting notes, in a section only accessible by the
staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enhanced-learning-futures"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enhanced Learning Futures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a full day of listening to tremendously interesting talks coming
straight from the classroom trenches, I felt the &amp;quot;capstone address&amp;quot;
resonated a bit hollow -- it was an excellent presentation but it nearly
felt too polished!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still Steve Wheeler brought up plenty of good ideas and food for
thought, regarding the direction society, technology and education are
going toward. Tools shape our behaviour, the more we use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of societal shifts: Amazon now sells more Kindle books
than paper books. 1.5 billion mobile phones have been sold. Girls are
catching up in terms of gaming trends. The gamification of learning can
lead to deeper learning because we want to repeat the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learners need to acquire &amp;quot;digital wisdom&amp;quot;. Lovely new term: darwikinism!
The survival of the fittest content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to next year's event :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="ireland"></category></entry><entry><title>Teaching Webcraft / Audience | Who are your learners?</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2012/01/teaching-webcraft-audience/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-01-30T21:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-01-30T21:19:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2012-01-30:/blog/2012/01/teaching-webcraft-audience/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/content/what-do-you-want-your-learners-to-learn/"&gt;second
task&lt;/a&gt;
for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/"&gt;Teaching
webcraft&lt;/a&gt;
course is about making up profiles for people we're hoping to help. The
couple of biographies that follow do not cover it all, but should still
be a fair sample :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;* * *&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jessie&lt;/strong&gt; is a high school student, and although she thinks about it
often …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/content/what-do-you-want-your-learners-to-learn/"&gt;second
task&lt;/a&gt;
for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/"&gt;Teaching
webcraft&lt;/a&gt;
course is about making up profiles for people we're hoping to help. The
couple of biographies that follow do not cover it all, but should still
be a fair sample :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;* * *&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jessie&lt;/strong&gt; is a high school student, and although she thinks about it
often, what she wants to do after her final year still very much depends
on what catches her interest the most any given week. She navigates the
web effortlessly, and hangs out online in all the social networks her
friends are into. She never really considered programming as something
she could learn, but when presented with the opportunity to join an
intro course she thinks maybe there she'll learn enough code to be able
to personalise her blog, and make it look unique and more interactive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course will teach Jessie how to create her first program, and that
programming is more similar to puzzle solving than inputting number in
Excel to do sums like in the ICT class. Perhaps something worth
exploring further...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jon&lt;/strong&gt; is working hard at his PhD thesis in social sciences. He has a
lot of statistics to parse and go through every day, results of
experiments to reproduce before building on them and so on. He has a
dozen of Excel spreadsheets set up with insane macros that save him a
lot of time, but still wastes many hours manually inputting data taken
from websites or articles. He's hoping learning to program will enable
him to spend less time on drudge work and more time exploring the
interesting questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course will teach Jon how to automate more of his experimental
work, and in the process make him realise there are other areas where
some scripting would make writing his dissertation more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paula&lt;/strong&gt; doesn't consider herself a power user, but she knows the
keyboard shortcuts for every application she uses, is familiar with the
file system layout of her computer (and learnt what a file system is)
thanks to a couple of misadventures clicking on interesting looking
icons, and is known to her friends and colleagues as the go-to person
whenever a computer misbehaves. Though she doesn't plan on making a
career out of it, she is curious to gain an understanding of what's
under the hood of all these applications she uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course will teach Paula the fundamental steps and &amp;quot;bricks&amp;quot; that
every program is made of, and help her understand why bugs happen and
what makes them difficult to eradicate. Maybe putting together a short
script to randomly assign secret Santas for the next Christ Kindle
wouldn't be too hard, though...&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="P2PU: Teaching webcraft"></category><category term="teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Teaching Webcraft / Compare your practices to IES report's recommendations</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2012/01/teaching-webcraft-ies-reports-recommendations/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-01-15T18:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-01-15T18:52:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2012-01-15:/blog/2012/01/teaching-webcraft-ies-reports-recommendations/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm taking an online course at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org"&gt;P2P University&lt;/a&gt;,
on &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/"&gt;How to teach webcraft and programming to free-range
students&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
taught by Greg Wilson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the initial comments on the course it's possible I
misunderstood what &amp;quot;free-range students&amp;quot; means ; from the course
description I took it to mean teaching in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm taking an online course at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org"&gt;P2P University&lt;/a&gt;,
on &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/"&gt;How to teach webcraft and programming to free-range
students&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
taught by Greg Wilson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the initial comments on the course it's possible I
misunderstood what &amp;quot;free-range students&amp;quot; means ; from the course
description I took it to mean teaching in various non-traditional
settings, but it might actually be specifically about online learning
(?). It's fine, the general concepts of &amp;quot;what is good teaching&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;how
people learn&amp;quot; and how to encourage independent learning will be helpful
anyway. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="first-task"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First task&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://p2pu.org/en/groups/how-to-teach-webcraft-and-programming-to-free-range-students/content/getting-started-some-things-to-read-some-things-to-think-about/"&gt;Our first
task&lt;/a&gt;
is to take a look at the IES (Institution of Educational Sciences)
report on &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ies.ed.gov/ncee/wwc/practiceguide.aspx?sid=1"&gt;Organizing Instruction and Study to Improve Student
Learning&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
(summarised in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://software-carpentry.org/2011/12/organizing-instruction-and-study-to-improve-student-learning/"&gt;Greg's post
here&lt;/a&gt;)
and compare their recommendations to our own approach to teaching
programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, I teach sporadically in my own time, to small groups of
6 to 10 complete beginners, usually-but-not-always adults, in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;local
hackerspace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-1-space-learning-over-time"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 1: Space learning over time.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arrange to review key elements of course content after a delay of
several weeks to several months after initial presentation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 or 6 weeks-long course, this can be difficult. However, most
concepts do build on top on each other: once learnt, they will be used
every week from then on. The later concepts could benefit from regular
review, but by then the course is about finished unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-2-interleave-worked-example-solutions-with-problem-solving-exercises"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 2: Interleave worked example solutions with problem-solving exercises.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have students alternate between reading already worked solutions and
trying to solve problems on their own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the 2nd session of the course, I start by showing a short, working
program to the class and ask them to think about what it could be doing,
(trying to) figure out as a group what could be its purpose. This sounds
more like review though, as it reuses the previous concepts. The report
also reads that &lt;strong&gt;alternating&lt;/strong&gt; working examples + exercises is hugely
important. &amp;quot;Worked example solutions&amp;quot; should go into much more details
than what I've been doing as well (showing intermediate steps, rather
than only the final solution).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-3-combine-graphics-with-verbal-descriptions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 3: Combine graphics with verbal descriptions.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Combine graphical presentations (e.g., graphs, figures) that illustrate
key processes and procedures with verbal descriptions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't say that I'm really doing this. I'm projecting code, sometimes
working out solutions in front of the class but this isn't particularly
graphical. I'm not sure how to do this either. It actually reminds me of
the approach to learning that Sean O'Leary mentioned in his talk on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sess.ie/resources/science-differentiation-action"&gt;differentiated
learning&lt;/a&gt; at
the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/05/reimaging-learning/"&gt;Reimagining Learning
conference&lt;/a&gt;,
where he told us about adding visual cues to quizzes and concepts to
help dyslexic learners and students with a more visual approach.
Although useful, this doesn't exactly match the IES report
recommendation which advocates making sure the graphical element is
directly relevant to the concept being taught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-4-connect-and-integrate-abstract-and-concrete-representations-of-concepts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 4: Connect and integrate abstract and concrete representations of concepts.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Connect and integrate abstract representations of a concept with
concrete representations of the same concept.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report explains that students gain an understanding faster when
using concrete examples, but then don't know how to transfer the
knowledge to new problems ; while students who learn the concept
abstractly struggle more initially but are then more flexible with the
knowledge. The report advocates mixing up both, which I'm not doing or
not doing well as my students tend to have trouble reusing previous
concepts to break down more intricate problems on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-5-use-quizzing-to-promote-learning"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 5: Use quizzing to promote learning.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use quizzing with active retrieval of information at all phases of the
learning process to exploit the ability of retrieval directly to
facilitate long-lasting memory traces.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5a. Use pre-questions to introduce a new topic.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't do this. I
wonder if &amp;quot;previewing&amp;quot; an unknown programming concept would help
learning, or increase confusion. It'd definitely need to solve a
concrete problem, ideally that we encountered in the previous session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5b. Use quizzes to re-expose students to key content.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't do
this either. (Actually, reading on the report, presenting small programs
and asking students to figure out what it does may be considered a quiz,
as it encourages them to retrieve previously learnt material). It's
interesting, and I wonder how to apply it to teaching practical
programming while keeping the questions short and meaningful (maybe tiny
programs with missing bits, with a multiple choice as to what to fill
the blank with?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-6-help-students-allocate-study-time-efficiently"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 6: Help students allocate study time efficiently.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assist students in identifying what material they know well, and what
needs further study, by teaching children how to judge what they have
learned.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6a. Teach students how to use delayed judgements of learning to
identify content that needs further study.&lt;/strong&gt; I'm not doing this, except
perhaps brutally when giving exercises that a student doesn't know how
to solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6b. Use tests and quizzes to identify content that needs to be
learned.&lt;/strong&gt; This advises giving a quiz, written or oral, could be done as
a game, right after presenting new material, so students can assess what
they actually do remember. I don't do this. Considering most of my
students don't make the time for homework or studying at home, I don't
know if this would be very effective on its own. Or perhaps it would
highlight that they do need to study outside of the class and encourage
them to do so...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="recommendation-7-ask-deep-explanatory-questions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendation 7: Ask deep explanatory questions.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use instructional prompts that encourage students to pose and answer
“deep-level” questions on course material. These questions enable
students to respond with explanations and supports deep understanding of
taught material.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do a tiny bit of this when I introduce a new concept or explain what
an existing program does, but not very deeply, nor involving the class
enough (it can be tough generating discussion!). Some of the suggestions
include having students think aloud, then comment and build on each
other's understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="P2PU: Teaching webcraft"></category><category term="teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Michel Thomas Method: Learning a language | Japanese Foundation Course</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/09/michel-thomas-method/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-09-08T20:11:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-09-08T20:11:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2011-09-08:/blog/2011/09/michel-thomas-method/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been using the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_thomas"&gt;Michel
Thomas&lt;/a&gt; Method to learn
Japanese lately, using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Michel-Thomas-Method-Japanese-Foundation/dp/0340974575/"&gt;this set of
CDs&lt;/a&gt;
(8 hours). It works wonderfully well. The method only claims to teach
you basic conversation skills, no writing or reading, and does so
without requiring you to learn long lists of vocabulary or really …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been using the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_thomas"&gt;Michel
Thomas&lt;/a&gt; Method to learn
Japanese lately, using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Michel-Thomas-Method-Japanese-Foundation/dp/0340974575/"&gt;this set of
CDs&lt;/a&gt;
(8 hours). It works wonderfully well. The method only claims to teach
you basic conversation skills, no writing or reading, and does so
without requiring you to learn long lists of vocabulary or really, do
anything outside of listening to the lessons. Each CD is cut into short
lessons lasting between 3 and 8 minutes, and all you need to do is
listen carefully and make use of the pause button to think of your
answer before hearing the correct way to say something. There're 2 other
students on the recordings, sometimes making mistakes and asking
questions. You play the role of the 3rd student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through non-boring repetition, you learn how to structure different
types of sentences and slowly add new words to your vocabulary. It's
very enjoyable and you get a great sense of accomplishment when you
remember things and figure out how to express something new. I usually
listen on the bus -- I found listening while walking didn't work as well
because a pedestrian needs to pay a lot of attention to their
surroundings in the city if they'd like to not die, so I wasn't focused
enough and ended up forgetting more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaflet that comes with the box is adamant that &lt;strong&gt;your learning is
the teacher's responsibility&lt;/strong&gt;. You shouldn't try to learn stuff off by
heart, or force yourself to remember or pick up new things in your own
time. That makes me wonder how this applies to teaching programming. How
much responsibility am I putting on the students to understand concepts,
and how could I judiciously apply repetition and questioning to make
people learn whether they want to or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is really how these language lessons work. If you're listening, you
have no choice but to learn. There's a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.audible.com/pd/?asin=B0036GTIUI"&gt;free sample of the Japanese
version&lt;/a&gt; and other
languages on Audible, if you're curious to hear how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Update: I also &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/10/learning-japanese/"&gt;posted on what I did after the Foundation
Course&lt;/a&gt;, and
ideas on what to do after finishing the Advanced Course)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Language_learning"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="japanese"></category></entry><entry><title>GTUG July meet-up: Google APIs &amp; panel on hackerspaces and formal education</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/07/gtug-july-meet-up/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-07-27T19:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-07-27T19:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2011-07-27:/blog/2011/07/gtug-july-meet-up/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening Google kindly hosted the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://groups.google.com/group/dublin-gtug/browse_thread/thread/606febbb094b184f"&gt;GTUG
meet-up&lt;/a&gt;,
which I don't usually attend but considering some of my fellow
hackerspace members were speaking on the panel I had to go and
*cough*heckle*cough* support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="google-storage-and-predictions-api"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Google Storage and Predictions API&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of the evening was a talk by …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening Google kindly hosted the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://groups.google.com/group/dublin-gtug/browse_thread/thread/606febbb094b184f"&gt;GTUG
meet-up&lt;/a&gt;,
which I don't usually attend but considering some of my fellow
hackerspace members were speaking on the panel I had to go and
*cough*heckle*cough* support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="google-storage-and-predictions-api"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Google Storage and Predictions API&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of the evening was a talk by Martin Omander on 2 Google
APIs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Storage API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure out what you're good at so that you can focus on that (don't
build your own telescope, use other people's tools). The Storage API is
what Google use themselves, therefore they have people on pager to make
sure it stays up so you don't have to. Libraries such as
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://boto.cloudhackers.com/"&gt;Boto&lt;/a&gt; work with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Predictions API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You feed it training data, over 3 steps: upload, train, predict. It can
do categorisation (for e.g. language recognition), or return a number
(e.g. real estate valuation). Input data can be text or numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="hackerspaces-and-formal-education"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hackerspaces and formal education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The juicy part of the evening was the panel, despite starting with a
very biased intro from the moderator against education in favour of
hackerspaces. Asking the panelists to choose a side might have also
contributed to limit the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A blurry picture of the panel" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2011/gtug.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 interesting topics straight from the panelists' introductions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To work around the lack of decent sysadmins around, John Looney from
Google has created a short graduate program, where they train people
for 5 months and then hire them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Whelton is a startup founder that is currently working on
&amp;quot;Coder Dojo&amp;quot;, a project to bring programming and computing to kids. I
had a quick chat with James after the panel and they are bringing
this to Ireland, starting in Cork: it seems their process is to find
mentors in a city, get the group started running
events/workshops/classes on a Saturday afternoon and then they move
on to the next city. I'm not quite sure it's a sustainable way to
build a momentum but I will be following this very very closely, and
perhaps mentor when they come to Dublin. Not entirely sure where to
get the freshest source of info: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/#%21/coderdojo"&gt;Twitter account
here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://codrcamp.com/"&gt;All Ireland (?)
blog&lt;/a&gt; over there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone mentioned Sugata Mitra's talk on learning without teachers
again, I have to make the time to watch this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of interesting points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hackerspaces as part of formal education, as a society, or part of
the University -- someone brought up the problem of evaluation and
how to grade work that would come out of such a setting; a panelist
remarked that academia has been doing that for decades, with PhDs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If going the society way, be careful to build a community. It should
help with getting momentum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there was a nice flow when only the panel and moderator were
speaking, I was disappointed with how the audience involvement and back
and forth with the panel was handled. Some questions were completely
ignored after being asked without giving a chance to the panel to
answer, and people talking were encouraged to speak faster or less as we
were running out of time. I would have preferred less questions explored
more fully, rather than a rush of comments and unresolved question
marks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everybody would agree there is much more to be discussed on the topic :)
Thanks to the organisers for setting this up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="ireland"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry></feed>