<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>jpichon.net - gnome</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 03:52:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Switching locale (Gnome 3, Fedora 20) | and making sure all the menus switch too</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2015/04/switching-locale-gnome-3/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of immersion, I switched the laptop's language to
Japanese, however most of the Gnome menus remained in English even after
switching the System Language altogether, logging out etc. Another
profile on the laptop shows the menus for Activities, etc in Japanese
just fine so it wasn't a missing package. I found the following in
~/.profile, which seems a bit heavy-handed but does do the trick. For
future reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
LANG=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LANGUAGE=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_CTYPE=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_NUMERIC=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_TIME=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_COLLATE=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_MONETARY=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_MESSAGES=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_PAPER=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_NAME=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_ADDRESS=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_TELEPHONE=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_MEASUREMENT=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_IDENTIFICATION=&amp;quot;ja_JP.UTF-8&amp;quot;
LC_ALL=
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note on restarting X one is asked if they want to change the names for
the default folders like Documents, etc. Personally I find it makes
using the CLI a pain and don't recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 03:52:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2015-04-19:/blog/2015/04/switching-locale-gnome-3/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>gnome</category><category>japanese</category><category>linux</category><category>open-source</category></item><item><title>"Making Your First Contribution To Open-Source" | Irish Hackerspaces Week 2011</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/08/making-your-first-contribution-open-source/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A CG character in front of a laptop thinking of various open-source projects" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2011/contributing_to_open-source.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave my presentation on &amp;quot;making your first open-source contribution&amp;quot;
in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt; yesterday evening and I think it went
down well; I enjoyed delivering the talk and received positive comments
about it afterwards -- although I do need to speak louder. I'm enjoying
lightning talks! Now, what to speak about next... :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides are available on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slideshare.net/jpichon/making-your-first-opensource-contribution"&gt;Slideshare&lt;/a&gt;
(or
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/presentations/2011_08_25_ContributingOSS_TOG.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;).
I also gave a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/presentations/2011_08_25_ContributingOSS_TOG_handout.pdf"&gt;hand-out&lt;/a&gt;
to give people a chance to check out the links afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;ul class="first"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;ul class="first"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another note I think an evening of lightning talks was generally well
received, and there is some motivation to run another similar event in 2
months. I'd love to have this be a regular thing. We need to be more
strict on time-keeping though; surprisingly it seems people tend to feel
bad for not speaking long enough, so they start just talking about
random stuff or opening web links of cool things to show off... and
interesting or not it feels like it's dragging on, particularly when one
knows there's 3 or 4 more talks to go after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got feedback from first time visitors that starting late &amp;quot;because
people will be late anyway&amp;quot; makes it very sucky for people who don't
know anyone yet, and also less likely that there'll be time to stick
around after the talks to chat with the speakers and other attendees. I
think we should start right on time next time (and to be fair, the 2 or
3 people who arrived between 7:00pm (announced time) and 7:30pm (actual
starting time) were members... Not worth waiting for!!). It'd be nice to
start on time and then encourage people to stay with drinks and cookies,
or otherwise we need to find a social butterfly that is good at
integrating people. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing this down now, so that I can remember it in 2 months. Any other
comments on the evening from people who were there, or general
suggestions and tips on organising lightning talks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2011/08/irish-hackerspaces-week-2011/"&gt;Irish Hackerspaces Week isn't over yet! Check out our other
events.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 21:15:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2011-08-26:/blog/2011/08/making-your-first-contribution-open-source/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>contributing</category><category>events</category><category>gnome</category><category>ireland</category><category>tog</category></item><item><title>Desktop Summit 2011 - Back!</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/08/desktop-summit-2011-back/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://desktopsummit.org"&gt;Desktop Summit&lt;/a&gt; is finished for me,
though it continues on with workshop and BoFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berlin's weather is pretty much like Dublin's with regard to the sky
colour and rain status; though maybe with a few more degrees :) I quite
enjoyed the conference, very happy to meet again the friends I made last
year as well as meeting up with new interesting people (btw, if you
asked about my card, it was made at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moo.com"&gt;moo.com&lt;/a&gt;:
get yours now!!). It was also great to meet a couple of cool people
whose activities I follow online, though I'd like to find a way to
introduce myself to someone I know who doesn't know me in a perhaps less
creepy way :o) (Sorry people, it was still a pleasure!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found less elation in the technical talks this year than last, perhaps
because it's difficult to beat the excitement of seeing Gnome 3 work for
the first time, pre-release. The ones I attended were still interesting
and hinted at all the solid work that is going on currently, and I
really enjoyed the many discussions on outreach, collaboration between
the projects and within projects, and all that goodness. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.desktopsummit.org/program/sessions/gnome-state-union"&gt;Gnome
State of the
Union&lt;/a&gt;
talk was a hoot, and one of the highlights for me was when they showed a
list of quotes from unhappy users, like &amp;quot;if they treat their users like
idiots, they should expect idiots as users&amp;quot; (or something like this),
etc., as we're seeing online at the moment. It turned out these quotes
were about the Gnome &lt;strong&gt;2.0&lt;/strong&gt; release, and this makes me hopeful once the
dust settles down, people will look at Gnome 3 with less of a knee-jerk
reaction (and might still decide it's not for them, of course).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try to put together my notes into a few posts, though I can
guarantee I won't have the time to be as thorough (or long-winded,
depending on the point of view!) as in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/tag/europython/"&gt;my notes for
EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; unless I get the
flu or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the organisers for putting together the conference and
parties, I had a great time -- s'y'all next year!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 16:47:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2011-08-10:/blog/2011/08/desktop-summit-2011-back/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>gnome</category></item><item><title>Desktop Summit 2011</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2011/08/desktop-summit-2011/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="I'm going to the Desktop Summit 2011" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2011/desktop_summit.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow morning at ass o'clock, I fly to Berlin to attend the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://desktopsummit.org/"&gt;Desktop
Summit&lt;/a&gt; \o/ The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://desktopsummit.org/program"&gt;talk
schedule&lt;/a&gt; looks fantastic and I'm
really looking forward to it, and to meeting again the friendly people
from last year as well as new friendly faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woohoo! See you there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2011 19:27:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2011-08-04:/blog/2011/08/desktop-summit-2011/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>gnome</category></item><item><title>GUADEC: Inside the Banshee Awesome Factory</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/12/guadec-banshee/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Eek! Looking through my old drafts I can't believe I forgot to post
this. I was waiting for the LWN link to become available to all -- but I
guess it's never too late to share the awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Article: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lwn.net/Articles/399296/"&gt;GUADEC: Banshee project reaches out for
contributors&lt;/a&gt; (LWN)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the summary of a very good talk, &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://guadec.org/index.php/guadec/2010/paper/view/95"&gt;Inside the Banshee Awesome
Factory&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; from
last GUADEC, describing a number of things that the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://banshee.fm/"&gt;Banshee&lt;/a&gt; project does to attract, welcome and
nurture new contributors. For instance, they make sure to make plugin
development fun, by automating away the boilerplate code -- kinda
similar to starting a new project in Django (I wonder if that's
something Sugar could use, to create new Activities...) Every
contribution is equally appreciated, including the &amp;quot;typo&amp;quot; fixes that
many people would start with. They're not afraid to welcome people with
little programming knowledge, and walk them through how easy it is to
fix a bug or add a new feature. I suspect this works fantastically to
also attract good people who are not overly confident in their skills.
The speaker wasn't scared to live-demo how easy it is to add a new
feature, particularly if it's similar to something existing -- actually
he was a very good speaker, if you have the time you might want to catch
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flumotion.com/first_webm_live_event.php"&gt;the video of the talk
itself&lt;/a&gt; (day 3,
Paris room, 10:15-11:00).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very cool stat I forgot about, that's in the article: in the last 2
years and a half of development, Banshee has averaged &lt;strong&gt;one new
contributor every week&lt;/strong&gt;. That is awesome! It's worth looking into what
it is they're doing right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 21:23:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-12-30:/blog/2010/12/guadec-banshee/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>contributing</category><category>events</category><category>gnome</category></item></channel></rss>