<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jpichon.net - sugar</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/feeds/tag-sugar.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jpichon.net/</id><updated>2010-08-17T22:46:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Oh, sweet! The Sugar learning environment</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/08/oh-sweet-sugar-learning-environment/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-17T22:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-17T22:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-08-17:/blog/2010/08/oh-sweet-sugar-learning-environment/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2010/08/irish-hackerspaces-week/#24"&gt;my talk in
TOG&lt;/a&gt; tonight.
I think it went quite well! I certainly got some positive feedback
afterwards. Lots of room for improvements still, of course, many &amp;quot;um&amp;quot;s
especially at the beginning, and it probably would have been better if I
had rehearsed more, to remove the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2010/08/irish-hackerspaces-week/#24"&gt;my talk in
TOG&lt;/a&gt; tonight.
I think it went quite well! I certainly got some positive feedback
afterwards. Lots of room for improvements still, of course, many &amp;quot;um&amp;quot;s
especially at the beginning, and it probably would have been better if I
had rehearsed more, to remove the attachment to my notes for prompts
when I got stuck, but otherwise it flowed well and people seemed clear
and happy on what Sugar was, what it looks like and the type of learning
it tries to encourage. Very nice audience, smallish and I knew most
people! Many interesting questions, and having 4 laptops running Sugar
(2 XOs with 0.82, 2 Eee with Mirabelle) for people to try out afterwards
was a hit, I was delighted to see people rushing toward them and trying
out all sorts of activities. (Delightful, noisy Tam Tam!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/08/presentation-zen/"&gt;Presentation
Zen&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; style of
presenting worked well too, I think, and I got a few questions about
this and the pictures I used. I still need to practice more and become a
stronger speaker to support this style better, though. (Motivated!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/presentations/2010_08_17_Sugar_TOG.pdf"&gt;presentation
slides&lt;/a&gt;,
for the curious. In true &amp;quot;Presentation Zen&amp;quot; style they are much less
useful without me chatting in front of them, but you'll find most of the
information I used for content on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sugarlabs.org"&gt;http://sugarlabs.org&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org"&gt;http://wiki.sugarlabs.org&lt;/a&gt; ! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="sugar"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry><entry><title>Hackerspaces Week</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/08/hackerspaces-week/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-07T18:10:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-08-07T18:10:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-08-07:/blog/2010/08/hackerspaces-week/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There hasn't been much public info about it yet, but inspired by
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chebe.dreamwidth.org/26743.html"&gt;Cheryl's Hackerspace Week
teaser&lt;/a&gt; I'm going to start
speaking about it too! The first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackerspaces.org/wiki/Irish_Hackerspaces_Week"&gt;Irish Hackerspaces
week&lt;/a&gt; will
happen soon in August, from the 14th to 22nd, and I'll be talking about
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sugarlabs.org"&gt;Sugar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My talk will last about …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There hasn't been much public info about it yet, but inspired by
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chebe.dreamwidth.org/26743.html"&gt;Cheryl's Hackerspace Week
teaser&lt;/a&gt; I'm going to start
speaking about it too! The first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackerspaces.org/wiki/Irish_Hackerspaces_Week"&gt;Irish Hackerspaces
week&lt;/a&gt; will
happen soon in August, from the 14th to 22nd, and I'll be talking about
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sugarlabs.org"&gt;Sugar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My talk will last about 30 minutes, in the evening of the 17th in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie"&gt;Tog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Come and learn about Sugar, the learning platform for children.
Sugar offers an innovative desktop environment designed to encourage
collaboration and critical thinking through Activities. Initially
developed as part of the One Laptop Per Child project, Sugar is now
community led and can run on any machine thanks to Sugar on a Stick.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be plenty of other interesting talks, workshops, demos and
&lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;... that I will happily link to once more information starts
surfacing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: It's alive! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tog.ie/2010/08/irish-hackerspaces-week/"&gt;Full schedule of the
week&lt;/a&gt; now
available.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="events"></category><category term="ireland"></category><category term="sugar"></category><category term="tog"></category></entry><entry><title>Contributing to an open-source project: Sugar, a newcomer's perspective.</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/06/contributing-to-open-source-sugar/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-06-02T23:01:00+01:00</published><updated>2010-06-02T23:01:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-06-02:/blog/2010/06/contributing-to-open-source-sugar/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's proven difficult to write up a summary of my experience as
someone-who's-not-a-hardcore-open-source-contributor-yet-but-certainly-plans-on-becoming-one.
There's an easy dialogue-killing answer to any anecdote I relate: &amp;quot;suck
it up.&amp;quot; I'm still trying to find a way to express all this though,
because I'm sure there's something to learn from any newcomer's attempt
to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's proven difficult to write up a summary of my experience as
someone-who's-not-a-hardcore-open-source-contributor-yet-but-certainly-plans-on-becoming-one.
There's an easy dialogue-killing answer to any anecdote I relate: &amp;quot;suck
it up.&amp;quot; I'm still trying to find a way to express all this though,
because I'm sure there's something to learn from any newcomer's attempt
to join a project, and also for my future self, when I'll be the one
encouraging others to get involved with open-source and won't remember
what it's like to stand on the edge, trying to understand how a
community functions and how to find a space that fits you in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. Two anecdotes on contributing to Sugar, then a description of the
incredible level of confusion I've been experiencing looking at the
development process overhaul, followed by some ponderings on &amp;quot;what's
next&amp;quot; which I better follow up on in the future :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="anecdote-1-fixing-a-bug-infoslicer"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anecdote 1: Fixing a bug (InfoSlicer)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sugar (and the XO!) had been on my radar for a while. Last summer I
finally made the time to set up sugar-jhbuild on my laptop and start
trying it out for myself. I was enthusiastic but despite the very good
wiki I wasn't sure where I could make myself the most useful (Sugar
core? Making a new activity? Fixing activity bugs?). I find fixing bugs
to be a fantastic way to get familiar with a project and a code base,
however I wasn't sure how to pick one because every ticket in
bugs.sugarlabs.org is already assigned to someone. It wasn't obvious to
me whether I was welcome to work on any or if there was some sort of
&amp;quot;please may I work on this bug&amp;quot; process or if assigned people might be
protective of their code (I've met a few virulent &amp;quot;It's my code/my bug!&amp;quot;
people before, albeit mostly in college.) The sugar-love bugs were few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enters &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ossbarcamp.com/"&gt;OSS BarCamp&lt;/a&gt; in September 2009,
where I met &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lauracowen.co.uk/blog/2009/02/19/presentinginfoslicer-educational-software-for-sugar/"&gt;Laura
Cowen&lt;/a&gt;
(thanks Jaime for pushing me to introduce myself!) who presented a
lightning talk on a Sugar activity, InfoSlicer. Having met with a real
person who was enthusiastic and sort of involved with Sugar, I thought
I'd take a look at InfoSlicer. There was only one bug filed against it
at the time, that quite seriously limited the capabilities of the
activity. I set out to fix it. A few weeks later, I was attaching my
patch to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugs.sugarlabs.org/ticket/1348"&gt;the ticket&lt;/a&gt;,
discreetly sweating over the associated comment. Someone replied less
than a day later, suggesting a different approach inspired after another
activity I hadn't heard about and before I had come back from work that
same day, the current maintainer had accepted my patch and also
suggested another way to do it that &lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt; could work on together. I was
double-elated and thanks to the &amp;quot;we&amp;quot; felt very welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I hadn't enjoyed a lot working on the parsing code for
InfoSlicer and despite promising myself I would update the activity with
the new toolbar &amp;quot;soon&amp;quot; I didn't get back to it (yet, shall we say. I'd
still like to do the toolbar thing sometime.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="anecdote-2-fixing-bugs-pippy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anecdote 2: Fixing bugs (Pippy)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'round the same time I had volunteered to show cool engineering things
to a transition year (high school) student spending a few &amp;quot;work
experience&amp;quot; days in my workplace. Although he was a bit older than the
Sugar usual demographics, I gave him a usb stick with Sugar on it
anyway: Sugar is &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; and we all had unrealistic expectations of what
a student could accomplish in a week. I thought perhaps he could get
familiar with the project then investigate a bug. After he showed some
curiosity about programming, I stirred him toward Pippy which he enjoyed
greatly despite the occasional stracktraces some examples were
invariably throwing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these issues had already been reported so I thought, &amp;quot;I love
Pippy, I'm gonna try to fix as many as I can.&amp;quot; Along the way someone I
know got a bit hyped up by my enthusiastic chanting of &amp;quot;Sugar Sugar
Sugar&amp;quot; and had set out to fix a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugs.sugarlabs.org/ticket/347"&gt;serious display
bug&lt;/a&gt; in Pippy, #347, despite
not being particularly fond of Python. I fixed a couple of other bugs,
attached the patches to the relevant reports and hopped away, waiting
for a review or update. Months went by. My friend lost interest. I began
to pep myself up to ask about the Pippy maintainer on IRC. At the time I
was trying to build up some confidence by getting my work accepted first
before going about and expressing opinions or asking questions in public
places (not the way people usually prefer things to be done in
open-source, I realise.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A series of coincidences happened and I suddenly was offered commit
access to the Pippy repository (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/03/commit-access/"&gt;I mentioned that
before.&lt;/a&gt;) Despite
the best intentions, I wasn't comfortable pushing my patches to the
mainline merely because I had the power to do so ; I find it preferable
and better for patches to be looked at and approved by people who know
what they're doing. Eventually I pushed
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dev.sugarlabs.org/ticket/843"&gt;#843&lt;/a&gt; myself into the mainline,
as Chris Ball kindly reviewed it as part of an email thread. I still
didn't feel so good about it, managing the statuses in Trac was unclear
(both status + resolution must be marked as fixed/resolved?) and the bug
never ended up assigned to me (it looked like Trac's button would change
both the status and assignee so I wasn't sure and then it was too late,
I didn't want to revert the status back.) Basically, as I've stated
before, I was still in dear need of a mentor, and I still didn't reach
out. I fully understand and accept that this is my fault for not
communicating well enough with the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another bug I had worked on, I didn't fix correctly the first time
around. When this was brought up I responded quickly, explaining where I
thought the issue was and submitting &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugs.sugarlabs.org/ticket/638"&gt;a second
patch&lt;/a&gt; a few days later. I
won't be pushing this to mainline until someone else confirms it works,
but I'm still happy with it because I proved (to myself, too) that in
case of problems I am responsive and able to correct issues within a
decent timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I was also getting fidgety about #347 as without it, Pippy is
impossible to use on my Eee and likely on other netbooks. Eventually I
asked, still within the bug tracker, if people would mind if I pushed
the current (working) patch to the mainline. Other unrelated
requirements had come up in the bug report discussion, much less serious
than does-not-work-at-all-unless-patch-is-applied so it felt fair to
push the partial patch. Lots of people had popped up the first time
around and subscribed to that bug, but there was no answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long after, someone submitted a duplicated patch to fix #347 as well
as the other unaddressed aesthetic issues, using a new process still
being defined. The patch got reviewed, no one mentioned the duplication
(I didn't either) and soon after the patch was pushed to the mainline
and the submitter became Pippy maintainer (yay! At least Pippy now has a
more active maintainer, hopefully!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's great to see movement on the Pippy front but I felt so disheartened
by the duplication of that patch that had been sitting there for 7
months and that I had to install manually on every stick I made for the
past 7 months. I invested so much energy running in circles like a
headless chicken, trying to do things right with my shiny commit access
and waiting for feedback. I was very discouraged, the basic lesson
being: I shouldn't have cared so much, especially when I knew I hadn't
fully groked all the processes yet. This only (mostly?) happened because
I did not reach out to the community through other channels than the bug
tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-new-process"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The new process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm at it, I'd like to mention what's going through my mind with
regard to development process changes that SugarLabs has been setting up
lately. Sugar is basically moving toward a mailing-list only style of
communication to submit patches and I've been endlessly confused since
this started. I'm not sure it's the most inclusive process either though
I understand the problems it's trying to solve -- mostly lack of code
reviews as illustrated by anecdote #2 :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's more confusing than it used to be and makes the barrier to
entry higher because as far as I can tell, now if I or anyone want to
fix a bug:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I go browse trac and find something interesting/that I care about to
work on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now I also have to search through my inbox and patchwork (a new
system I haven't totally figured out yet either, but it doesn't look
any less confusing than my inbox with every patch/email thread thrown
in there together) to see if the bug is already being worked on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to join the mailing list to submit my patch (I'm assuming, but
it's probably necessary if you want to be sure to get the answers) --
that's quite intimidating and a commitment for &amp;quot;just&amp;quot; a patch. The
process should also be easy for passersby if you want people to stick
around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading the mailing list and the patches as they get submitted is also
confusing because it's difficult to link a patch to a bug and understand
the background/context. In most cases you'd have to go and dig it back
up from the bug tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know people are working on it at the moment, so I will wait for the
wiki to be updated with clear instructions on how to effectively use the
new process and systems, as the wiki still only describes how to work
with trac. For now I'm watching perplexedly and wondering if really, the
mailing list will be the only way for people to contribute in the
future? I worry that the new process is inspired from projects that
focus on hardcore technical people (Linux kernel) rather than others
that also welcome passionate beginners
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://denise.dreamwidth.org/23600.html"&gt;Dreamwidth&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other valid solutions were proposed to fix the patch review problem and
I wish I had found the bug on re-creating a &amp;quot;patch need review&amp;quot;
automatic weekly email so I could have tried to do my bit to help. Great
Sugar contributors believe in the new process though, enough to invest
their time setting it up and setting up the tools to make it work more
conveniently. Now that I've finally written this post and digested what
happened and where I messed up, I should be able to focus on how I can
help the project with other contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-now"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step back, start from scratch with a clean state of mind. Probably stay
away from code contributions for a bit. Talk with the community. Stop
messing up brilliant opportunities when introduced to cool people by
email ;) Be more pushy when it comes to asking for feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the releases notes surrounding Fedora 13 and Mirabelle make
me hopeful: the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/Sugar_on_a_Stick"&gt;Sugar on a Stick (Mirabelle) wiki
pages&lt;/a&gt; are awesome,
vibrant with optimism and that sub-community within the community sounds
like a great way into main Sugar. Quote from their wiki I love: &amp;quot;When
you're stuck, and have spent more than 15 minutes trying to figure out
what to do next [, email the mailing list / ask on IRC].&amp;quot; The weekly
meetings where newcomers are welcome sound like a good idea as well, it
gives some structure rather than let new people break into the main
group on their own (or so I imagine, I wasn't able to attend the first
meeting last Monday.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry><entry><title>Commit access | Contributing to Sugar</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/03/commit-access/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-03-16T22:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-03-16T22:56:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-03-16:/blog/2010/03/commit-access/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Through a series of kinda mind boggling coincidences, meeting people and
talking about what I have in mind and am passionate about, earlier this
month I ended up with commit access to the Pippy activity (a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sugarlabs.org"&gt;Sugar&lt;/a&gt; application). Wow! Awesome. A few
weeks back, I had decided to fix as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Through a series of kinda mind boggling coincidences, meeting people and
talking about what I have in mind and am passionate about, earlier this
month I ended up with commit access to the Pippy activity (a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sugarlabs.org"&gt;Sugar&lt;/a&gt; application). Wow! Awesome. A few
weeks back, I had decided to fix as many of the broken examples as I
could after getting a bit embarrassed showing off Sugar to a teenager,
last October. He was very interested but as we were using Pippy it felt
like we were getting stack traces a bit too often (they weren't that
many really, they just happen to be more memorable.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I fixed them and the patches sat there for weeks (I didn't set the
&amp;quot;need review&amp;quot; flag to be fair, which I just discovered in a corner of
the wiki last week), along with a patch not-from-me in #347 which I
think should really-really make it into the next release because Pippy
is completely unusable on my (all?) netbook without it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I've been granted the Power Of The Commit so it should all be fine,
with me committing away and happily making the world a better place...
but it's not so simple, because really, I'm still living too far away
from the community to understand how they work and notably here, the
interactions with and within the bug tracker. For instance, I didn't
realise you were supposed to add the &amp;quot;r?&amp;quot; keyword when submitting a
patch, I found it accidentally when looking for something else in the
wiki. I'm not a maintainer either, so it's not entirely clear what I
should be doing with the bug report after submitting a patch or the
process to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although my patches are tested and too small (I believe!) to actually do
great damage, I didn't commit them... which ended up being a good idea
since one of them was incorrect :) Someone kindly commented on the bug
report saying it didn't work, with details. Turns out I was so keen on
removing the stack traces I didn't check if the error messages provided
by other Pippy examples were actually correct (so I display &amp;quot;install
this&amp;quot; instead of showing a stack trace, but the &amp;quot;install this&amp;quot; doesn't
actually solve the issue for that example, nor for the example I took it
from.) I've now attached a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugs.sugarlabs.org/ticket/638"&gt;new, better
patch&lt;/a&gt; to the report (...and
set the proper review flag!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's probably a tad too early for me to have those commit rights, just
yet. I need a mentor still, except individually everybody is incredibly
busy being awesome already, which is fair. The truth is, I already have
a mentor if I reach out to it: the community. So this is always
something I will be working on in parallel, I really want to integrate
with the community. It just takes time for someone not so comfortable
with the &amp;quot;public speaking effect&amp;quot; of pouring thoughts, mistakes and
ideas on public, sometimes archived mailing lists and channels. I'll
figure it out, at my own pace. I have access to some pretty cool people
individually in the meantime if I really need help. My first area of
focus is grokking the bug tracker so I can contribute effectively there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sugar-stuff-i-want-to-figure-out"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sugar stuff I want to figure out:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to know when a patch is big enough to warrant the &amp;quot;r?&amp;quot; flag, or
really should they all have it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The complete process for submitting a patch. Right now, I think, a
lot of the information I am looking for is under the &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/Development_Team/Code_Review"&gt;Code
review&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
wiki page which makes it not obvious to find, and it's still not a
clear step-by-step process. As I progressively get a better
understanding of how things work I'd like to improve on it and/or
eventually make a case for a &amp;quot;Submitting patches&amp;quot; page aimed at
brand-new contributors, ideally &amp;quot;drive by&amp;quot; contributors too. I'm
thinking of something along the lines of Gnome's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://live.gnome.org/GnomeLove/SubmittingPatches"&gt;&amp;quot;Submitting
patches&amp;quot; page&lt;/a&gt;,
or Gnome's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://live.gnome.org/Empathy/Git"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://live.gnome.org/Tomboy/HowToSubmitPatches"&gt;specific&lt;/a&gt;
guidelines, which I found really useful when I was getting ready to
make my first open-source contribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out what developers do with bug reports, the best practices. How
keywords and the 5.000 status/milestones/etc fields are being used
and who gets to set them. I suspect there's probably an established
set of guidelines for Sugar core, and that activity maintainers kinda
do their own things, but still, I'm sure a set of best practices has
emerged, somehow, somewhere. Usually &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/BugSquad/Triage_Guide"&gt;triaging
guides&lt;/a&gt; are
pretty good at indicating how the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/BugSquad/Status_Fields"&gt;status
field&lt;/a&gt; should
be used and what it means up to a certain point (usually, up to when
the developer takes charge of the bug which is when I started getting
stuck) but for Sugar, what I've seen so far doesn't seem to match the
wiki (for instance there are a lot of bug marked assigned that aren't
being worked on, and I suspect they just automatically get assigned
to the maintainer or something like this. To be investigated
further.) Also for the non-creator/non-main-maintainer of a
component, is it ok to simply close off a bug after pushing a patch,
even if no one else confirmed it worked? (I guess any problem will
bubble back up to the bug tracker anyway, eventually...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code freezes. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.sugarlabs.org/go/0.88/Roadmap"&gt;We're in one
now&lt;/a&gt;, but I'm not sure
how this impacts activities or if this is mostly about Sugar core,
and when/which/how a version of an activity is selected to be shipped
with the current release (and does that differ for &amp;quot;main&amp;quot;/fructose
activities like Pippy?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry><entry><title>Contributing</title><link href="https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2010/01/contributing/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-01-31T00:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-01-31T00:22:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpichon</name></author><id>tag:www.jpichon.net,2010-01-31:/blog/2010/01/contributing/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article is about a year old, but it doesn't matter: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.webchick.net/embrace-the-chaos"&gt;Diaries of a Core
Maintainer #6:) A tale of two developers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reading that story is always a bit scary and cause for
self-reflection because my approach is so similar to Pat's, particularly
when starting out with a new idea …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article is about a year old, but it doesn't matter: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.webchick.net/embrace-the-chaos"&gt;Diaries of a Core
Maintainer #6:) A tale of two developers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-reading that story is always a bit scary and cause for
self-reflection because my approach is so similar to Pat's, particularly
when starting out with a new idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could say I'm posting this now for people considering getting involved
with an open-source project but afraid to jump in, or ask questions, or
wondering if they're good enough, and that's usually what I send it to
people for but... this time, what I really want if for more people to
know about it, so they can send it back to me when I really need it!
It's okay not to know everything or get things perfectly right the first
time. It's ok to learn new things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For nearly two weeks, I've been sitting on a (tested!) Sugar patch
because I don't fully understand the intricacies of &amp;quot;why it actually
works&amp;quot; (xterm magic, there'll probably be a post about that soon!). I
probably still would be digging into the entrails of xterm, tty and
whatever other dead-ends I keep losing myself into for this bug, had
someone not reminded me of this story. The patch is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dev.sugarlabs.org/ticket/843"&gt;now
submitted&lt;/a&gt;, right beside a
comment explaining where I'm stuck and asking for help. Looking forward
to the next step :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you know why a xterm control sequence documented since at least
1994 could be sending back an abridged output on a different (but
recent) hardware / software stack, please do let me know...&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="contributing"></category><category term="open-source"></category><category term="sugar"></category></entry></feed>