<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>jpichon.net - Tech</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 21:58:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>ShipItCon 2024</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2024/08/shipitcon-2024/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;To avoid taking a year again to (fail to) put my notes together, I decide to do
it quickly and stick to a few thoughts and highlights. The 2024 edition of
&lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/"&gt;ShipItCon&lt;/a&gt; happened today. This year's theme was "Flow." Many speakers
mentioned ownership when talking about ways to reach flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't attended many conferences in the last couple of years, but maybe 90%
of the people I talked to were also meeting their co-workers face-to-face for
the first time at this event, despite working together for years. At least
three different companies. I found it interesting. It doesn't look like there
are many opportunities for teams to meet outside of conferences at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ShipItCon welcome slide" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2024/shipitcon2024.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;DevOps Topologies 10 years on: what have we learned about silos, collaboration, and flow? (Matthew Skelton)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker kindly summarised his findings both at the start and the end of the
talk: decouple teams and tech (not just defining an org structure, something
more dynamic), but diffuse learning across the company (that can take the form
of Lunch and Learns, blogs, Communities of Practice, guides, etc...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading recs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gene Kim's books (the Phoenix Project, Accelerate, ...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SODOR, the State Of DevOps Reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Organisation, Flow, and Architecture (Sam Newman)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an incredibly dynamic and engaging speaker! The theme was generally how to
reduce handoffs, which happens particularly when organisation are siloed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conway's law: An organisation design systems that replicate the communication
structure of that organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you have Taylorism-inspired silos with e.g. separate
front-end/back-end/DB teams, the system will reproduce that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution is feature-based teams (micro-services are good to enable full
ownership). Durable as opposed to initiative-based teams are also better as
long-lived teams make better decisions about trade-offs (e.g. incurred tech
debt, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Data Driven Decisions to Improve Testing Flows (Heather Reid)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using data to take risks. Differentiating between reversible and not reversible
risks. The speaker used various examples based on her own experiences to
illustrate the principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example: closing an old bug to remove noise is easily reversible if it
turns out it shouldn't have been closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 1000s of users report a problem, it can feel like millions/all of your users
are hitting the problem. But maybe when you look at the data it's 0.6% of the
userbase, which is still bad but not world-ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or a really bad bug affecting 6 users using that phone model (out of millions)
can probably be closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prioritise accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Observability 2.0 and other things (Charity Majors)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The title isn't on the agenda and I forgot to write it down!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tip for how to supercharge your career: join a high-performing team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineering should own the code in production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observability is a property of complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observability-driven development means looking at your dashboards (as opposed
to waiting for alerts/paging to bring them up). It's a constant conversation
with code (including unstructured logs, not just metrics, because they provide
CONTEXT). (Higher level: structured logs with trace ids you can follow end to
end.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Establishing a culture of ownership and observability at Phorest (Paweł Malon and Paul Dailly)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the speakers use Honeycomb which is the observability platform
of the previous speaker. It was like seeing practical examples of the concepts
detailed in the previous talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of engineering owning the code all the way to production came up
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And also, of linking engineering workflows to observability: deploying a change
and seeing what difference it makes, and conversely using the insights gained
from observing software behaviour on prod to find new bugs/improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a lot of metrics does create issues with the cost of storing all of that
data, which is where sampling helps, although the speakers talked about the
other problems you then have to deal with when sampling and how to manage them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Go With The Flow? (Vessy Tasheva)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play is a component of flow. Venn diagram of Play and Environment with Flow
where the circles meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environment: must be safe even if there are constraints/discomfort. E.g. a
leader having your back when working on a challenging project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play is a way to be more authentic and creative. "Being" (which respects focus
time) vs "Reacting" (which breaks flows and creates defensiveness).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Flow-etry in Motion: Navigating Cascades of Threat Data (Claire Burn)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting twist to the talk! When the speaker submitted it, it was supposed
to be about how their pivot to using Kubernetes and Google Cloud Platform
enabled better flow in the team. But by the time the conference happened, they
had reverted back to AWS and EC2!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no "peak flow" to be found because Kubernetes wasn't the right tool
to solve their problems (they needed finer grained OS control).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considerations around Learning Curve vs Velocity, especially when working as a
smaller team (4 people). The management debt became too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did end up keeping Kotlin from this experiment, good for integration with
other Java projects in the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The impact of Flow on various aspects of work (Panel discussion)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beat_Saber"&gt;Beat Saber&lt;/a&gt; as a way to get into flow 😂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed teams are good for making the implicit explicit. Managing based on
outcomes. The additional flexibility is good for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honeycomb has a quarterly "everyone works from home" week, up to the CEO. It's
good to get distance from processes, etc. (I thought that was a refreshing
contrast to all the Return To Office talk from the last couple of years.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many problems are socio-technical: need a combination of tech and people
solutions, not just one or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Harnessing Developer Insights to maximise flow (Mihai Paun and Alma Tarfa)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learned helplessness in companies: "we've always done it this way" "that's
never going to work here."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the picture of the Iceberg of Ignorance, from &lt;a href="https://www.corporate-rebels.com/blog/iceberg-of-ignorance"&gt;Corporate
Rebels&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Iceberg of Ignorance" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2024/iceberg-ignorance.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papercuts affecting flow tend not to surface in retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Plan - Do (gather data) - Check (target condition) - Act&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, they found their dev team struggled to reach flow state because of
the number of meetings, so they decided to try setting up two no-meetings day
(Monday, Wednesday) then gather data to see if that helped. Everyone involved
in the four steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small changes toward reaching the bigger goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders: be gardeners, not mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From MLOps to AI Systems (Jim Dowling)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most AI systems don't ship. This hasn't changed in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MLOps, LLMOps. He explained when he teaches a ML course, his students complete
an AI project from scratch in 2 weeks. It doesn't need to be as complicated as
30+ steps diagrams/consultants make it out to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While looking for a link to the course, I came across this &lt;a href="https://www.hopsworks.ai/post/mlops-to-ml-systems-with-fti-pipelines"&gt;detailed
article&lt;/a&gt; that goes into the details of the talk if that is of interest. And
includes a link to the students' projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Finding personal flow (Patrick Kua)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal flow usually comes from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adding value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a lot of ownership (with support)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a sense of progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;applying the team's strengths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker used past experiences to illustrate various kind of very different
environments that can lead to good flow. This actually linked back nicely to
Vessy's earlier talk as well: challenging projects but in a safe
environment/with support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anecdotes I liked was when he was trying to remove himself as a
bottleneck in a large project, he broke down the features, and asked if anyone
would step up as feature leads for each of those. People had no problem
volunteering and that also links back to ownership again. And feature-based
teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of putting up notes early is that the recordings are not yet
available!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Julie Pichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 21:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2024-08-30:/blog/2024/08/shipitcon-2024/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>ireland</category></item><item><title>ShipItCon 2023</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2024/08/shipitcon-2023/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/"&gt;ShipItCon&lt;/a&gt; 2024 fast approaching (in 2 days!!), it's time for me to
admit I will never finish writing up my notes from last year's and just post
what I do have. Perhaps this year my note-taking skills will improve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ShipItCon is a small non-profit conference in Dublin that focuses on Software
Delivery. The conference is a single track on a single day, and the theme in
2023 was "The Unknown" (observability came up A LOT!). Here are of a few of the
highlights, from my perspective (and from my very, very partial notes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/recordings/?_sfm_year=2023"&gt;2023 recordings&lt;/a&gt; are available now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keynote: Dr Norah Patten&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspiring journey to become Ireland's first astronaut! Also very
impressive and massive amount of outreach work. Including writing a
children's book, &lt;a href="https://app.thestorygraph.com/books/fbb5ee56-d40e-48f3-b2d2-34c7e84493e0"&gt;Shooting for the Stars&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked how she broke down several stages of her life into categories:
Influences (e.g. teachers, family) / Role models / Peers / Experience
(e. g. a visit to NASA as a child), and how each contributed and came
together to allow her to come to where she is, now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cool outreach projects I didn't know about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanoracks"&gt;Nanoracks&lt;/a&gt;, students plan experiments for astronauts then examine
  the results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://possum13.org/about/"&gt;PoSSUM 13&lt;/a&gt; for researchers, and the microgravity challenge for payload
  experiments in space/suborbital/microgravity. High school students apply with
  detailed plans of the science experiment they want to run, and if successful
  get to build the payload themselves with mentoring, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's Slowing Your Team Down? (Laura Tacho)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After observing hundreds of teams, the speaker found that every team has the
same problems, divided into three categories: projects, processes, people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker uses thousands of metrics to determine issues. Tracking doesn't
solve the problem but it helps with tracking progress as well as "quantify
sentiment" which I found really interesting. In general, I found this talk
incredibly informative and valuable, and I recommend the recording.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too much work in progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the biggest problems for most teams. It causes issues with getting
things done or finishing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measures that can help: number of projects per person (engineer cognitive
load), ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of prioritisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No means "not now"; yes means "forever" (with an every increasing maintenance
cost).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal should be specific enough that teams can easily say no to things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slow feedback (from people or machines)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not enough focus time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Length and frequency of focus time chunks, number of meetings where something
is actually at stake, ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. People&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unclear expectations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving expectations vs fear of micromanagement.
&lt;br/&gt;Receiving expectations vs fear of seeming incompetent, psychologically
unsafe teams.
&lt;br/&gt; (How this can set up a negative circle where one lead to the other and
back)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading recommendations: "Accelerate" (about DORA metrics), the SPACE of
Developer Productivity, &lt;a href="https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3595878"&gt;DevEx: What Actually Drives Productivity&lt;/a&gt;
(interesting, although at least one of the main author is selling something
related).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine the recording is available now, and the &lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/2-Laura-Tacho-Whats-Slowing-Your-Team-Down_-ShipItCon-2023.pptx"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; are also
interesting for a more detailed summary with many more examples of measures for
each category, and a link to the kind of developer survey they used to
"quantify sentiment."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building scalable GenAI Retrievial Augmented Generation Platforms (Mihai Criveti)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLM and their limitations. Text generation, doesn't learn from interactions, AI
function to predict the next word, doesn't access the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Models with 70 billions parameters cost $20k/month dedicated GPU instance on
Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/3-Mihai-Criveti-Retrieval-Augmented-Generation-v3.pdf"&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt; with more information on this works and the limitations the speaker
found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Make Your Automation a Better Team Player (Laura Nolan)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This felt particularly relevant to my work. The talk was really engaging
because the speaker always links every issue back to famous incidents or
incidents she personally experienced. The &lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/4-Laura-Nolan-Making-your-Automation-a-Better-Team-Player.pptx"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; also include these
examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Joint Cognitive Systems" where computers and humans collaborate on cognitive
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paper recommendation: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ironies_of_Automation"&gt;Ironies of Automation&lt;/a&gt; by Lisanne Bainbridge. 40yo
paper and these problems still haven't been solved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem described is like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The easy stuff is automated first&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New people only ever learn the hard stuff, and develop a partial
   mental model of how things work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life becomes harder for operators because they need to learn both
   how things work + how the automation works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are doing a bad job if the operator can shoot themselves in the foot with
our tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two anti-patterns to avoid!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Automation surprises&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automation through using a lot of scripts, tools, cronjobs is hard to
manage. Centralising into a self-running/autonomous automation helps, where
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The behaviour should be as simple and as predictable as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unattended upgrades are a bad idea, silent and deadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incident examples (although there are many! Linked in the slides, all
informative):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://firefish.social/notes/9iqefgi8rzfksnqc"&gt;routine GitOps operation&lt;/a&gt; (link now defunct :() that caused a
  namespace to be deleted when ArgoCD system lost visibility on the yaml,
  bringing down the entire site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.datadoghq.com/blog/2023-03-08-multiregion-infrastructure-connectivity-issue/"&gt;Unattended upgrade disaster&lt;/a&gt; at DataDog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Recommendation systems (e.g. to assist in troubleshooting.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They make it harder to generate alternative hypothesis. Using softer language
may help, like "in the past, problems like this were caused by X."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools as amplifiers: help with understanding systems, as opposed to providing
suggestions. They shouldn't hide complexity. Help operators to build a mental
model of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://shipitcon.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/4-Laura-Nolan-Making-your-Automation-a-Better-Team-Player.pptx"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; include links to more advice and lots of incident examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's it, because the talks were too interesting and I'm apparently unable
to be concise when taking notes. The conference is really excellent at inviting
deeply knowledgeable, deeply interesting speakers, and I'm looking forward to
the next one. Thankfully I won't have to wait long ;)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Julie Pichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 20:12:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2024-08-28:/blog/2024/08/shipitcon-2023/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category></item><item><title>Extracting reviews from Goodreads into Markdown pages</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2023/05/extracting-reviews-from-goodreads-into-markdown-pages/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In early 2020, it became really difficult to read books. I'm slowly starting to
get past that at last, but while Goodreads was super fun for a few years, right
now tracking and counting and rating just makes reading feel like a chore and
Not Fun as a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still would like to keep a record of what I read, though. And I used to write
&lt;a href="/tag/book-review/"&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt; on this blog before getting onto
Goodreads. It seems like a nice way to keep a record of what I read without it
becoming a number thing. I'll probably still write Goodreads reviews for small
authors since I know it can help, but I feel less pressed about having
everything there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to save the reviews I wrote only on Goodreads here, and wrote a
script to migrate my reviews into Pelican-friendly Markdown pages since that's
what powers this blog now. I decided to keep to a single entry per year
rather than one entry per book, since I had a few good reading years in there
(and others will only a single review!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Step 1: CSV export of the books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you go to 'My books' and find the 'Tools' menu at the bottom of the
leftside menu on Goodreads, you'll find a page to &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/import"&gt;export your
library&lt;/a&gt;. You may have to try a couple
of times: my first export only had a handful a books, the second one looks more
comprehensive although the number of books was off by two, but what can you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Step 2: Python script to create the Markdown pages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the script I wrote to extract only the books I've actually read. I
don't really care about DNF (did not finish) and to-read, right now. I also
hardcoded the years relevant to me. May someone find something helpful in here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;csv&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;dataclasses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataclass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@dataclass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;date_read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;rating&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;get_reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;goodreads_library_export.csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;csvfile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;reader&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DictReader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;csvfile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;row&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;row&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Title&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class="n"&gt;row&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Author&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class="n"&gt;row&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Date Read&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class="n"&gt;row&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;My Review&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;row&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;My Rating&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]))&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ne"&gt;ValueError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# When the int() cast fails, usually it means the CSV is&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# corrupted for that line. In my case, it was for a few to-read&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# records so I ignore them rather than attempt to fix the&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# original CSV. You can print the row here if you want to check&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# what&amp;#39;s failing.&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;

            &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;None&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;date_read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;rating_or_review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# If I wrote a review, return that&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Otherwise, make the rating into words.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rating&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;I really enjoyed it.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rating&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;It was fine.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Wasn&amp;#39;t for me.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;format_reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;book-reviews-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;.md&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;w&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Title: Book reviews: Year &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Date: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;isoformat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;tags: book review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# A couple of abandoned books sneaked in with a &amp;#39;0&amp;#39; rating, and I&amp;#39;m&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# not interested in preserving those&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rating&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;## &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rating_or_review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2013&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Chronological order&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;sorted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;date_read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;format_reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reviews&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part was probably to decide what text to convert a rating into,
since I didn't want to keep numbers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Step 3: Checking the output looks right and recalling fond memories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/year_in_books/2022/"&gt;'Year in Books'
pages&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads to
compare the results. There was some funkiness sometimes, like a book read in
2011 showing in year in books but without any shelves and a date read showing
as 2020, even though I don't remember messing with it. The review also shows as
Jan 2020 on the Goodreads UI despite appearing in the correct 'Year in
books'. 2020 turned out to be &lt;code&gt;date_added&lt;/code&gt; (which is definitely false) while
the &lt;code&gt;date_read&lt;/code&gt; field is empty. Maybe some data migration funkiness on the
Goodreads side at some point during the last 12 years. Otherwise, a duplicate
once, and a couple of intra-Goodreads links that didn't work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have to clean up the file for 2022. I was getting annoyed with tracking
myself so I didn't write reviews, but if it's for the blog I wouldn't mind
adding a few notes. And I need to decide if I want to post my 2023 reviews as I
go, or batch them in some way!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Julie Pichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2023-05-07:/blog/2023/05/extracting-reviews-from-goodreads-into-markdown-pages/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>python</category></item><item><title>Moving to Mastodon</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2022/11/moving-to-mastodon/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Three years since my last post, haha. And a couple of hardware failures in the
meantime, too. Let's see if I remember how to get set up with Pelican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dropped off Twitter a while back, but Mastodon is giving me hopeful vibes
(could just be the "new-to-me site" feeling, of course!). Either way, wanting
to add a link to my &lt;a rel="me"
href="https://mastodon.ie/@jpichon"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt; profile and get rid of the
Twitter one has motivated me to dust off this repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels &lt;em&gt;nostalgic&lt;/em&gt; to see a RSS feed link in my footer. I suspect I'm not the
only one hungering again for a more decentralised web again. Or more like, it
never went away but it got a lot less visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've got some notes from EuroPython (it was in Dublin \o/) I'll dust up soon,
and maybe I can start publishing my notes on the meetups I go to now that we're
all allowed outside again. Get back in the blogging habit... It could happen!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My apologies to long forgotten Planets this may appear in, haha, remove this
blog freely!! Tags have their own RSS feeds as well
(&lt;a href="https://www.jpichon.net/feeds/tag-open-source.rss.xml"&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No plan to add back a commenting section but feel free to chat on Mastodon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Julie Pichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 20:22:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2022-11-22:/blog/2022/11/moving-to-mastodon/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>open-source</category></item><item><title>UXDX 2018</title><link>https://www.jpichon.net/blog/2019/10/uxdx-2018/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whoops! Clearly I'm never going to finish writing up my notes for the
conference last year. Better post what I got even if incomplete, before the
next one begins :-) I couldn't get a discounted ticket this year and won't be
attending. Have fun, everyone there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be able to attend &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://uxdxconf.com/"&gt;UXDX&lt;/a&gt; this
year as well, thanks to a discounted ticket and my employer kindly allowing me
the day off. The venue was again the RDS, with the lovely room that's lined up
with actual real books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UXDX is an interesting conferences, that aims to bring down barriers between
User Experience and Developer Experience people. The conference has expanded
this year, now covering two days. I was happy to see some issues I had with the
conference last year resolved. For example, although the stated goal is to
bring together UX and DX people, improve collaboration, etc, the tracks were
completely separate. Worst for the DX-centred talks, the &amp;quot;room&amp;quot; was a stage at
the back of the exhibition hall and all the noise that entails. This year, the
separation between the two tracks was labelled &amp;quot;Vision&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Execution&amp;quot; which
made it easier to have talks mixing everything together, and also the Execution
room had a proper room with doors that close. The room was larger than the
section assigned last year too, and always full whenever I peeked in. Both
tracks were always busy. The exhibition hall seemed pretty empty outside of the
breaks, but there were plenty of those - staggered to lessen the lunch/coffee
rush.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="51%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="49%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td rowspan="2"&gt;&lt;img alt="Library room" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2018/RDS.jpg" style="width: 330.0px; height: 247.50000000000003px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td rowspan="2"&gt;&lt;img alt="Books" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2018/RDS_books.jpg" style="width: 330.0px; height: 247.50000000000003px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a handful of talks I was looking forward to, some met my expectations
and others turned out different. Many other good surprises. I'll summarise some
of the talks I enjoyed the most and only include my key takeaways for
others. This doesn't mean any of it was the actual point or meat of the talk,
more like the insights that were new to me personally and that I'll be
ruminating on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-one"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="micro-frontend-architecture-luca-mezzalira-dazn"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Micro Frontend Architecture | Luca Mezzalira (DAZN)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the day in the Execution room (it sounds a bit dramatic phrased like
this) and didn't really know what to expect with this talk, but it may have
ended up being my favourite one. The speaker stated his problem clearly - how
to make it work with hundreds of distributed developers/teams - and also noted
that the solution he came up with challenges common software development
wisdom, but to keep an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is to share absolutely nothing. Not even a button. &lt;strong&gt;Don't&lt;/strong&gt; create a
library of shared components, like headers. Really, how often does your header
change anyway? Trust your developers. They can duplicate and maintain this. The
goal is to minimise dependencies. Don't centralise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest is structured based on &amp;quot;Domain-Driven Development.&amp;quot; Each team has
their own domain (e.g. Catalogue, Subscription, Payment, ...) and completely
independent technology stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quicker on-boarding, because you only need to understand your own domain
deeply&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to scale teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom for developers to innovate and own something end-to-end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also mentioned the positive impact on turnover. In London, it's apparently
not uncommon for developers to change company every year, year and a half. This
makes it easy to try new technology which is often the main reason to jump
ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are frameworks that enable this nowadays, like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://single-spa.js.org"&gt;single-spa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://frint.js.org"&gt;frint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="planning-your-agile-architecture-will-demaine-fat-llama"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Planning your Agile Architecture | Will Demaine (Fat Llama)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an excellent talk, and well delivered as well. The speaker described
the steps you may want to follow to modernise your application and enable a
more agile architecture, from lessons learnt first hand through different
companies. If I had to undertake a project like this I think I'd find the
slides or recording again to refresh my memory first, but for today my key
takeaways would be that this is a long process that you want to tackle
iteratively, so that you can continue to deliver &lt;strong&gt;business value&lt;/strong&gt; along the
way. No one will let you just take off and deliver nothing new for 8 months
while you rewrite the thing from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have solid foundations in place (monitoring, feature flags, ...) before
starting. Take your time and do it right the first time or they won't let you
migrate more services!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point I found interesting: create a gateway for the clients, the things
that you can't roll back like mobile apps. Even if it's just a proxy to start
with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="embracing-empathy-tim-hudson-adyen"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Embracing empathy | Tim Hudson (Adyen)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pie charts bad. Bar charts good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Also, look into the Design Sprint / Design Sprint 2.0 books.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="solving-problems-to-build-a-compelling-product-deborah-clarke-cartrawler"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solving Problems to Build a Compelling Product | Deborah Clarke (Cartrawler)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User research is vital but not the only important thing. Combining with other
incentives can lead to better focus and great breakthroughs. Innocuous, small
moments of delight can increase your conversion rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-journey-from-complexity-reducing-technical-debt-fabrizio-fortunato-ryanair"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Journey from Complexity: Reducing Technical Debt | Fabrizio Fortunato (Ryanair)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting to follow the evolution of the RyanAir front page over the decades!
Some tidbits I found of interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact of page load. Any speed increase has a direct impact on revenue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use &amp;quot;micro-pages.&amp;quot; Concept similar to micro-frontend except it relates
to full pages, each page is its own app. So everyone is only responsible for
their own page independently, and loosely coupled. Single SPA per page, that
can be released independently but still has shared components (interesting
contrast with micro-frontend above).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They eventually wrote two different apps for mobile and web, as optimising
for one over the other never quite worked and only served in increasing
complexity. Now optimised for each flow. Still haven't decided whether to use
mobile or web format on tablets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use GraphQL, serverless, Brotli.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="design-and-prototyping-david-hoang-one-medical"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Design and prototyping | David Hoang (One Medical)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prototypes should be low cost and provide high insights. The goal is
learning. Having a prototype together with a vision/roadmap is powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Validating&amp;quot; a prototype or design is about gaining insights. About
learning. Not about proving something right or wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design is not magic, it's a rigorous process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include User Testing in every sprint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prototyping is successful if you get &lt;strong&gt;insights&lt;/strong&gt; that provide &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; to
your user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examples related to medical applications were compelling. From paper
(e.g. stuck onto a 3d printed watch model, to test for smart watches ahead of
releases), to powerpoint, to node-based prototyping, to Figma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-tools-we-use-challenging-dogma-in-the-design-process-emmet-connolly-intercom"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The tools we use: Challenging dogma in the design process | Emmet Connolly (Intercom)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools influence output, and can even generate trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use these tools and remain sceptical, don't let the tools push you around and
end up with a design monoculture (noticeable in the history of the web).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Design Ops&amp;quot; - a concept I hadn't heard of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ensuring-the-success-of-your-remote-engineering-team-panel"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ensuring the Success of your Remote Engineering Team | Panel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked that the conference kept the talks to 30 minutes, but I think
that's one case where it would have been better to get an extended timeslot,
maybe 45 minutes. As it stands even with only two panelists (+ one moderator)
we barely had time to scratch beyond the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping a budget for internal face-to-face interactions, some kind of annual
get-together has a great impact on morale and engagement and pays for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of saving on office space is not the point (numbers like
€17,000/person in Dublin, €11,000/person in Sligo were mentioned). Talent is
the point. Working remotely helps to attract and retain people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onboarding strategies were briefly touched on. One of the companies hires
mainly senior people with 10y+ experience while the other also hires new grads
so the strategies are different. It's great if you can get people to HQ for
this, makes sure they understand the company's values and culture, and also the
tools at their disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep people connected, having non-work related communication channels like a
#showyourdesk Slash channel or &amp;quot;whose view is better this week?&amp;quot; can help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time zones are a challenge for global meetings. Some expectation that you will
go the extra mile for the business, since you are not tied to a regular 9 to 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were concerns about working from home and whether people are really
working. In general the opposite seemed to be a concern for the panelists: when
people work from home you can't see the black bags under their eyes, or if
people are stuck. People know working from home is a privilege and work hard to
prove themselves. One of the companies measures employee productivity to make
sure they don't burn out - though you have to be very careful about how you
measure people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret sauce is flexibility. Work is only one part of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about accountability and self-determination? Decisions should be made by
the person who needs to. Empower people. Get that right. Measure what you want
success to look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regard to people not contributing, teams are tight and it becomes obvious
who is and who isn't. You do need to be more proactive in searching for
information with remote teams. One-on-one meetings every two weeks to touch
base. They are still refining the process. Seven seems to be a magic
number, you can see if people are performing for any type of team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="accessibility-brian-dalton-aer-lingus"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accessibility | Brian Dalton (Aer Lingus)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I missed the beginning but seeing how a user who relies on accessibility
features uses a computer and navigates the Internet is always powerful. Lots of
work to be done still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From keyboard to navigation to simple, silly things like &amp;quot;times shown in red
are not available.&amp;quot; Label your fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="five-phrases-that-shout-your-agile-isn-t-scaling-tony-grout-atlassian"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Five phrases that shout your agile isn't scaling | Tony Grout (Atlassian)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agile manifesto 17 years ago didn't talk about how to scale it! From 17 to
70000 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some interesting suggestions that challenge conventional wisdom. My favourite:
it's well-known that smaller teams are more productive. Studies have shown that
teams of 9 to 16 people were 6% less productive than teams of 5 to 9. However,
if you decide to make 2 teams instead you now have &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt; the unpredictability
because you've added a dependency on another team. Think carefully, run the
experiment to see if bigger teams may be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage people to think about &amp;quot;teams&amp;quot; over &amp;quot;team.&amp;quot; For example, if the UI
team is currently the bottleneck, instead of engineering twiddling their thumbs
or overengineering something while they wait, perhaps they could create tooling
to help the team. That slows them down and helps the other team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One team working faster can cause everyone else to go slower. For example, a UI
team wanting to be pixel perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those closest to the problem should make the decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="kessel-run-a-digital-transformation-story-within-the-world-s-largest-bureaucracy-adam-furtado-kessel-run-u-s-air-force"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Kessel Run: A Digital Transformation Story within the World's Largest Bureaucracy | Adam Furtado (Kessel Run / U.S. Air Force)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting choice for a closing keynote for day one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transformation described is absolutely incredible. The speaker spent a fair
amount of time at the beginning to explain the current state of things,
years/decades of risk aversion leading to becoming unable to adapt to change
and thus less safe. Twelve to fifteen years to go from an idea to something in
the users' hands, 96% of project behind schedule or over budget, 40% never
delivered... They went to Pivotal, who helped them to learn about modern
software development practices, devops, etc but more importantly how to change
the culture. Now deploying is a non-event and they went from 10 years to 120
days for delivering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's truly inspiring and the project they presented as an example showed the
real-world benefits: allowing soldiers to stay safe at home and with their
family rather than go on months-long refuelling missions around the world,
thanks to streamlining the refuelling planning process with
software. Definitely a worthy goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was however a bit strange to hear about software described as a
differentiator and weapon to cultivate on the battlefield, and how to improve
warfare. I suppose keynotes are meant to make you think rather than just give
you warm fuzzy feelings, and this talk sure fit the bill!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Courtyard" class="align-center" src="https://www.jpichon.net/site_media/images/2018/RDS_courtyard.jpg" style="width: 600px; height: 450px;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-two"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day Two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was just as interesting, too bad I left it too long to get the rest of my notes
together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">jpichon</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 07:24:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.jpichon.net,2019-10-07:/blog/2019/10/uxdx-2018/</guid><category>Tech</category><category>events</category><category>Ireland</category></item></channel></rss>